<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title><emphasis>QTaste User Manual</emphasis></title>

  <bookinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2014</year>

      <holder>QSpin SA</holder>
    </copyright>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>

        <date>02/10/2009</date>

        <revdescription>
          <para>First version for Open Source Release</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>

        <date>29/03/2012</date>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Minor updates (QTASTE_JYTHON_LIB), update some url for
          sourceforge</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>

        <date>25/09/2012</date>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Minor updates for release 1.2</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Introduction</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Why QTaste ?</emphasis></title>

      <para>QTaste framework (QSpin Tailored Automated System Test
      Environment) is a generic test environment customizable to test
      different kind of systems. It can be used to test simple and complex
      hardware or software systems including a lot of different technologies.
      For that reason, the test api has to be “tailored” in order to enable
      the kernel to communicate with your system.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Purpose</emphasis></title>

      <para>This document describes the installation and configuration steps
      of the “QSpin Tailored Automated System Test Environment” (QTaste). It
      provides useful information to the test designer and to the developer in
      order to define a new test script to be used by the QTaste
      framework.</para>

      <para>The test designer is responsible for writing test scripts based on
      the requirement documents. Associated to this task, the developer needs
      to provide a set of verbs that can be used by the script. The developer
      is responsible for the development of the newly defined QTaste verbs.
      Those activities must be performed with respect to the QTaste
      architecture.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Definitions, Acronyms and Abbreviations</emphasis></title>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec align="justify" colname="c2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Term</entry>

              <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Acceptance criterion</entry>

              <entry>Set of expected results expected at the output of the
              system when specific test data are provided. These can be exact
              values, ranges, probabilities, ...</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Actual outcome</entry>

              <entry>Contains a brief description of what the tester saw after
              the test steps have been completed. This is compared to the
              expected results in order to decide if the test is
              Success/Fail.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Agent</entry>

              <entry>Agents are active objects.They are capable of performing
              operations. Such agents may be software agents, hardware
              devices, or humans. They read inputs and generate outputs
              supposedly according to their requirements.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Automated testing</entry>

              <entry>Execution of tests without the intervention of the
              tester. Limited intervention of the tester for the introduction
              of results that are not available through interfaces, protocols
              and middlewares are possible during automated testing.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Control script</entry>

              <entry>A control script is a shell script able to start or stop
              a System Under Test (SUT).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Developer</entry>

              <entry>Person implementing some component, hardware or software
              and their stubs.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Environment</entry>

              <entry>(Sub-)set of systems, modules and components needed to
              perform a specific execution of a (sub-) set of operation of the
              original and complete system.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Expected results</entry>

              <entry>is a description of the results of the successful
              execution of a test case</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Failure</entry>

              <entry>in case of a failure, the software does not do what the
              user expects, according to the validation rule</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>GPL</entry>

              <entry>The GNU General Public License (www.gnu.org)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Input data</entry>

              <entry>is a set of values for input variables of a test
              case</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Intrusive, non-intrusive and low-intrusive test
              methods</entry>

              <entry>Intrusion means that the test is not using the public API
              of the tested component. Low-intrusion means that the behaviour
              of the component has been changed using the public API of a
              sub-component.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>LGPL</entry>

              <entry>The GNU Lesser General Public License
              (www.gnu.org)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Manual testing</entry>

              <entry>Execution of tests that are requiring the interaction of
              the tester or the test designer, to request some operation, to
              introduce test data, to introduce test results or to introduce
              validation rules.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Nominal cases</entry>

              <entry>Test case that is likely to happen during the nominal
              exploitation of the system.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Non-nominal cases</entry>

              <entry>Test case that may happen during the exploitation of the
              system during a fault or a degradation</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Open Source</entry>

              <entry>source code is provided</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Proxy</entry>

              <entry>A class functioning as an interface to another thing. The
              other thing could be anything: a network connection, a large
              object in memory, a file, or some other resource that is
              expensive or impossible to duplicate.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Requirement</entry>

              <entry>Is prescriptive statement of intent about the system to
              be, to be enforced by a single agent of the system-to-be through
              actuation of the variable under its control.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Simulated environment</entry>

              <entry>Environment that is using simulated and dummy
              (sub-)systems, modules and components.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Stub</entry>

              <entry>A piece of software or hardware that mimics the activity
              of a missing component</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>SUT</entry>

              <entry>System Under Test</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test API</entry>

              <entry>is the API providing methods to test a system or
              component and check the results</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test bed</entry>

              <entry>the aggregate of system under test, the test system, and
              the simulated environment.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test campaign</entry>

              <entry>is a predefined set of test suites or test cases that
              will be executed in order to get feedback about the quality of a
              system.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test case</entry>

              <entry>is a scenario composed of a sequence of actions and
              validations under which a tester will determine if a requirement
              or use case upon an application is partially or fully satisfied.
              It may take many test cases to determine that a requirement is
              fully satisfied.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test data</entry>

              <entry>is a set of values for test cases, used as input data and
              as expected results</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test Designer</entry>

              <entry>Person designing the tests to be executed on the QTaste.
              This person has a good understanding of the system under
              test.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test environment</entry>

              <entry>Synonym of test bed</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test Extension</entry>

              <entry>is an extension to the Test API mainly used for Stress
              Test in order to « break » some components.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test log</entry>

              <entry>is a log of all the test verbs that have been executed
              and of their actual results</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test management tool</entry>

              <entry>is a tool used to define and organize test cases, test
              data, test suites to perform a test campaign. It helps the
              tester to do the follow up of the test results.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test report</entry>

              <entry>is a report containing the result of the execution of a
              test suite</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test script</entry>

              <entry>is a short program written in a test-dedicated
              programming language used to test part of the functionality of a
              software system. It mentions a set of steps that should be
              performed in order to execute the test case.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Test suite</entry>

              <entry>is a collection of test cases</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Tester</entry>

              <entry>Person executing the tests defined by the Test Designer
              on the QTaste. Less skills are required than for the Test
              Designer, notably, he should not need to be an expert of the
              system under test in order to perform the tests.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Use case</entry>

              <entry>is a technique for documenting the requirements of a new
              system or software change. Each use case provides one or more
              scenarios that convey how the system should interact with the
              end user or another system to achieve a specific business goal.
              Use cases typically avoid technical jargon, preferring instead
              the language of the end user or domain expert. Use cases are
              often co-authored by requirements engineers and
              stakeholders.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Validation</entry>

              <entry>Checking that the behaviour of the system under test
              matches the expected behaviour, as described by its
              requirements.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Validation rule</entry>

              <entry>Rule checking if the expected behaviour and the actual
              outcome are identical or are matching acceptance criterion
              (parametric check)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Verb</entry>

              <entry>is an abstract definition of a functionality of the test
              API</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Overview of the QTaste framework</emphasis></title>

    <figure>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste “Overall system architecture overview”</emphasis></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure1.png" format="PNG"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Requirements, taken from a requirement management tool or from a
    document are derived into Use cases and Test scripts specific to the SUT
    business.</para>

    <para>Test scripts correspond to a sequence of Test API calls expressed in
    python scripting language. Each call corresponds to an operation or to a
    validation. Test cases are the combination of test scripts and the
    associated data.</para>

    <para>An operation consists of a set of actions on the system under test.
    Validation consists of a check enabling the validation of a previous set
    of operations.</para>

    <para>In order to support a data driven approach, Test Data are stored
    independently of test scripts in a CSV (Comma Separated Values)
    file.</para>

    <figure>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste “Example of python test script”</emphasis></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="res/user_manual/figure2.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste “Example of test data”</emphasis></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure3.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The table contains a list of columns names and associated values
    used by the Test scripts as inputs or expected outputs. These values are
    defined by the test designer. The values can correspond to a string input,
    numeric values, date, file path or any other kind of data format such as
    ranges or fuzzy information.</para>

    <para>Each line of the sheet corresponds to a specific test with
    predefined data. It may correspond to the “nominal case” scenario or it
    could be a set of data that will lead to an expected failure (e.g. value
    out of range) for “non nominal case” scenarios.</para>

    <para>The combination of the test script and the test data allows the test
    designer to generate tests cases that will be run by the test engineer
    using QTaste. The creation of the test cases is a shared responsibility
    between the test designer and the developer, as specific formalism and
    functions might be required in order to allow the Test Engine to correctly
    parse and execute the complete sequences.</para>

    <para>Once the test cases are executed by QTaste, test report is generated
    giving the result of the test case execution.</para>

    <figure>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste “Example of test report (part 1)”</emphasis></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure4.png" format="PNG"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste “Example of test report (part 2)”</emphasis></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure5.png" format="PNG"
                     scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>The QTaste Test-API parent</emphasis></title>

    <para>Each testapi have to inherit of testapi-parent component. This is
    used to make the internal qtaste dependencies available to the custom
    testapi. It is also used to share the configuration of maven plugins.
    (like plugins for the testapi documentation, etc)</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Overview of the QTaste directory structures</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste kernel directories</emphasis></title>

      <para>The following directories are located in the QTaste root
      directory.</para>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec align="justify" colname="c2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Directory</entry>

              <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>bin</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains scripts to start the test engine,
              generate documentations and start simulators</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>conf</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the configuration files</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>kernel/target</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the QTaste kernel jar</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>lib</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains all the shared libraries (dll and
              so) required by the QTaste framework</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>tools</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains all the shared libraries (dll and
              so) required by the QTaste framework</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test specific directories</emphasis></title>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>

          <colspec align="justify" colname="c2" colwidth="2*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Directory</entry>

              <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Testbeds</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the testbeds configuration
              files</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Testbeds/ControlScripts</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the control scripts associated to
              the testbeds</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TestCampaigns</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the test campaigns description
              files</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TestSuites</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains different test suites containing
              test scripts and test data</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>log</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains execution logs of the QTaste
              framework. It will be automatically created after the first
              execution of the Test Engine</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>reports</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the test reports generated by the
              Test Engine</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>testapi/target</entry>

              <entry>This directory contains the QTaste TestAPI jar and the
              generated HTML TestAPI documentation (in TestAPI-doc
              subdirectory)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Using QTaste framework</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test automation workflow</emphasis></title>

      <para>In order to develop new test cases using the QTaste framework, it
      is really important to understand the following points:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">
           Identification of the architectural components of the SUT and their interfaces that will be used to perform the tests. Which technologies are required to communicate with the components interfaces?
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Are the components testapi already implemented in QTaste? Are the technologies required to communicate with components already supported by the QTaste?
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Do the components have the required verbs to perform the operations and checks?
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           What are the parameters required to perform operations on the components? Identify variables that can be used as “Test Data”
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           What configuration parameters of the testbed are required in order to use the components in any testbed configurations?
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Design the QTaste components interfaces and develop component implementations
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Develop the python test script(s)
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Add rows in the “Test Data” to test specific cases
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Execute the test suite(s)
        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           Analyse the test reports and report test failures
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Starting the test engine</emphasis></title>

      <para>The command to execute a test suite or test script is:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">
           ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtaste_start.bat (or qtaste_start.sh for Unix platform) which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin
      directory in your path.</para>

      <cmdsynopsis>
         Usage:

        <command>
          <replaceable>command</replaceable>
        </command>



        <arg choice="req">-testsuite
        <replaceable>testsuiteDirectory</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="req">-testbed
        <replaceable>configFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-sutversion
        <replaceable>SUT_version</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-engine
        <replaceable>engineFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-loop [<replaceable>count</replaceable> |
        <replaceable>hours</replaceable>h]</arg>


      </cmdsynopsis>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="justify"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>

              <entry>Parameters</entry>

              <entry>Presence</entry>

              <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>-testsuite</entry>

              <entry>testsuiteDirectory</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>Specify the directory containing the testsuite(s)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-testbed</entry>

              <entry>configFileName.xml</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>Specify the testbed configuration file to be used for the
              test.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-sutversion</entry>

              <entry>SUT_version</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify the SUT version that will be reported.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-engine</entry>

              <entry>engineFileName.xml</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify the engine configuration to be used for the test.
              By default, the file conf/engine.xml is used.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-loop</entry>

              <entry>None | &lt;count&gt; | &lt;hours&gt;h</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify to execute the test suite in loop, respectively
              infinitely, &lt;count&gt; times or during &lt;hours&gt;&gt;
              hours.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>


      <title><emphasis>Starting the meta-campaign launcher</emphasis></title>



      <para>A meta-campaign specifies a set of testsuites or testscripts to be
      executed on specified testbeds. Optionally, the number of times they
      must be executed can be specified as well as the test data rows for
      which a test script must be executed.</para>



      <para>The command to execute a meta-campaign is:</para>



      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem
        override="bullet">${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtaste_campaign_start.bat (or
        qtaste_campaign_start.sh for Unix platform)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

       which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.

      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin
      directory in your path.</para>



      <cmdsynopsis>Usage:<command>
          <replaceable>command</replaceable>
        </command> <arg choice="req">campaignFileName</arg> <arg
      choice="opt">-sutversion
      <replaceable>SUT_version</replaceable></arg></cmdsynopsis>



      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="justify"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>

              <entry>Parameters</entry>

              <entry>Presence</entry>

              <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry/>

              <entry>campaignFileName</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>Specify the name of the XML campaign file</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-sutversion</entry>

              <entry>SUT_version</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify the SUT version that will be reported.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>



      <para>The format of the campaign file is the following:</para>



      <literallayout>&lt;campaign name="Campaign_Name"&gt;
   &lt;run testbed="testbedName.xml"&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="testSuiteDirName"&gt;
         [&lt;testdata selector="commaSeparatedListOfRowId"/&gt;] (optional, to
                execute scripts only for specified test data rows; row id starts at 1)
         [&lt;count&gt;numberOfTimesOrHoursToExecute&lt;/count&gt;] (optional, to execute in loop)
         [&lt;loopInHours/&gt;] (optional, if numberOfTimesOrHoursToExecute is in hours)
      &lt;/testsuite&gt;
      &lt;testsuite …&gt; … &lt;/testsuite&gt;
      …
   &lt;/run&gt;
   &lt;run …&gt; … &lt;/run&gt;
   …
&lt;/campaign&gt;</literallayout>



      <para>Here below an example of campaign file:</para>



      <literallayout>&lt;campaign name="Campaign example"&gt;
   &lt;run testbed="enginetest.xml"&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_SCRIPT"/&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_KERNEL/QTaste_RES_06"&gt;
         &lt;testdata selector="1,4,5"/&gt;
         &lt;count&gt;2&lt;/count&gt;
      &lt;/testsuite&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_01"/&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_04"/&gt;
      &lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_05"/&gt;
   &lt;/run&gt;
&lt;/campaign&gt;</literallayout>


    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Starting QTaste graphical user interface</emphasis></title>

      <para>The QTaste Graphical User Interface can be used in order to
      interact with the QTaste test engine and QTaste test campaign.</para>

      <para>The command to execute QTaste with its GUI is:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">
           ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/ qtasteUI_start.bat (or qtasteUI_start.sh for Unix platform)
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>which must be run from the test specific directory containing the
      directories specified in section 4.2.</para>

      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin
      directory in your path.</para>

      <cmdsynopsis>
         Usage:

        <command>
          <replaceable>command</replaceable>
        </command>



        <arg choice="req">-testsuite
        <replaceable>testsuiteDirectory</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-testbed
        <replaceable>configFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-engine
        <replaceable>engineFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>



        <arg choice="opt">-loop [<replaceable>count</replaceable> |
        <replaceable>hours</replaceable>h]</arg>


      </cmdsynopsis>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="center"/>

          <colspec align="justify"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>

              <entry>Parameters</entry>

              <entry>Presence</entry>

              <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>-testsuite</entry>

              <entry>testsuiteDirectory</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>Specify the directory containing the testsuite(s) to use
              when the GUI is started. So using this parameter, a test suite
              is launched.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-testbed</entry>

              <entry>configFileName.xml</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify the testbed configuration file to select, if not
              specified the last used testbed is selected.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-engine</entry>

              <entry>engineFileName.xml</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify the engine configuration to be used for the test.
              By default, the file conf/engine.xml is used.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>-loop</entry>

              <entry>None | &lt;count&gt; | &lt;hours&gt;h</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Specify to execute the test suite in loop, respectively
              infinitely, &lt;count&gt; times or during &lt;hours&gt;
              hours.This parameter is only taken into account when the
              parameter testsuite is also specified.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>HTML test report document</emphasis></title>

      <figure>
        <title><emphasis>QTaste "HTML Test reports”</emphasis></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure6.png" format="PNG"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
             An example of HTML test report
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Some additional remarks about HTML test reports document:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">
           The versions of the test scripts may be extracted from a version control tool (like subversion repository as example) during the execution of the tests. The version of will be reported only if:

          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <listitem>the subversion command-client (“svn”) is available in
            the PATH</listitem>

            <listitem>testsuites are used in a svn repository and are a
            “tagged” as version. (rely on svn URL).</listitem>

            <listitem>The engine configuration file (conf/engine.xml) tag
            &lt;version_control&gt; is configured
            properly.(com.qspin.qtaste.util.versioncontrol.impl.SubversionVersionControl)</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>



          <para>The version will be set to “undefined” in all the other
          cases.</para>


        </listitem>

        <listitem override="bullet">
           SUT version field is coming from either the SUT version field if the test is started from the QTaste GUI or the “-sutversion” parameter if started from the command-line.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test API Documentation</emphasis></title>

      <para>The HTML Test API documentation is automatically generated by the
      maven Test API projects, in the target/TestAPI-doc subdirectory and is
      accessible from the GUI (see Figure XXX: Navigation buttons).</para>

      <figure>
        <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test API documentation"</emphasis></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure7.png" format="PNG"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
             Test API documentation
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Additional Java libraries</emphasis></title>

      <para>If for some reason, QTaste needs additional libraries, they can be
      specified through the environment variable QTASTE_CLASSPATH. These
      libraries will be automatically added to the class path and available
      during the QTASTE execution.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>QTaste Graphical User Interface</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Starting tests</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>QTaste user interface startup</emphasis></title>

        <para>The command to start the QTaste User Interface is the following:
        ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtasteUI_start.bat (or qtasteUI_start.sh for Unix
        platform) which must be run from the test specific directory
        containing the directories specified in section 4.2.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Testbed management</emphasis></title>

        <para>For first startup a default testbed is selected, otherwise the
        last selected testbed during previous sessions will be selected by
        default.</para>

        <para>The user can change the testbed for which test must be executed
        by using the dedicated combo box displayed in the Information
        panel.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Current selected testbed"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure8.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
               Current selected testbed
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>When a testbed is selected, the current selection is stored in
        the preferences file (${QTASTE_HOME}/conf/gui.xml) in order to select
        it by default at the next launch.</para>

        <para>A contextual menu is available on this list to view or edit the
        testbed configuration file.</para>

        <para/>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Testbed selection"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure9.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test suite execution</emphasis></title>

        <para>From the selection panel where the test cases are displayed,
        select the test case (Figure 9: test case execution) or test suite to
        execute (Figure 10: Test suite execution), then press on the "Execute
        test"' button (Figure 11: Execute test button).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test case result analysis</emphasis></title>

        <para>The tab "Test Case Results" is automatically displayed when the
        executed test is started.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test Case Results panel"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="res/user_manual/figure12.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The test case results panel displays the following
        information:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>- Summary of the test case execution status;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>- Error details when test case is failed</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>- Stack trace when test case is failed</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>- Log4j panel displayed QTaste logs</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>When a test case result is failed (or Not available status), the
        corresponding icon is displayed. By selecting the row, the error
        details and the available stack traces will be displayed.</para>

        <para>From the Error details, the user can double click on the row and
        the Python editor will be opened at the line of the detected error.
        This is available for any python script except for the one having the
        file name "embedded_jython" which is built dynamically by QTaste
        during the test execution.</para>

        <para>By selecting test case result row, the Log4j panel will point to
        the first log associated to the test case. For more details about the
        use of the Log4j panel filters, please refer to</para>

        <para>It is possible to re-run a specific test case row (or several
        rows) using the popup menu on the test case result row, and select
        "Re-execute test(s)". Copy the details of the error in the clipboard
        or generate a test campaign from the test in errors.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Re-execute test(s) pop-up"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure13.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste main window</emphasis></title>

      <para>When the QTaste GUI application is started, the main window is
      displayed (Figure 14: Main QTaste User Interface window).</para>

      <figure>
        <title><emphasis>QTaste "Main QTaste User Interface window"</emphasis></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure14.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This main window is split into the following panels:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Menu items</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Information panel: this panel located at the upper side is
          designed to display useful information about the current
          configuration of the QTaste software</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Selection panel: this panel is designated to select an action
          to be performed by QTaste. This panel is subdivided into three
          different tabs:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Test case tree view: this view displays the list of
              available test suites that can be executed by QTaste</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test Campaign view: from this window, test cases can be
              added or removed to a test campaign</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Interactive view: this view allows the tester to execute
              QTaste verbs independently of a test script in order to validate
              its implementation or to observe the SUT behavior once the
              selected verb is called</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Main panel: this panel is the main view of the QTaste GUI.
          This view differs depending on the selected view from the selection
          panel.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Test case main panel: from this view the tester can view
              or edit test scripts, run a test suite, check the status of the
              test execution and also the logging generated by QTaste and its
              component supporting this feature.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test Campaign editor panel: from this view the tester can
              define or modify test campaign. The result of this edition will
              result of a xml file that can be used by the test campaign (see
              Starting the Meta-Campaign launcher); From this panel it is also
              possible to start a selected test campaign.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Interactive panel: from this panel status and results of
              the calls done using QTaste interactive mode is displayed</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Menu items</emphasis></title>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Help menu content"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure15.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Help menu</emphasis></title>

        <para>Two menu items are available:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>About: display the QTaste information</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>User Manual: open Internet browser to this document in HTML
            version.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Information panel</emphasis></title>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Information panel window"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure16.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This panel displays the following information:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Test suite currently set</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Test result directory location (relative to QTaste main
            path);</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Reporting format used (separated by “|” if different reports
            format generated by the test engine);</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Testbed config: indicates the current testbed selection.
            When no testsuite is being executed, it is possible to change the
            testbed using the combo box.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Ignore control script: by selecting this check box, when
            test engine is started, the control script defined in the testbed
            configuration is ignored.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Restart testbed button: from this button, it is possible to
            start the testbed using the control script as it is defined in the
            testbed configuration file. This button is disabled when “Ignore
            control script” is not selected or when a test is being
            executed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Stop testbed button: from this button, it is possible to
            stop the testbed using the control script as it is defined in the
            testbed configuration file. This button is disabled when “Ignore
            control script” is not selected or when a test is being
            executed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>SUT version is used to set the version of the “System Under
            Test”. This will be present in the generated reports.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Selection panel</emphasis></title>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Selection panel"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure17.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This selection panel displays 3 different tabs depending on the
        desired action:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>“Test case selection view” to perform actions linked to test
            case edition and execution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>“Test Campaign view” to define and edit test
            campaigns</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>“Interactive view” in order to execute tests using the
            interactive mode of QTaste</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case selection view</emphasis></title>

          <para>From this window, the tester can navigate through the
          different test suites. The tree view displays directories found in
          the main directory TestSuites. All directories containing a
          TestScript.py file will be displayed as a test script with the name
          of the directory where the script is found.</para>

          <para>In case no associated TestData.csv file is defined or in case
          the csv file is empty, an error icon is displayed on the test
          script.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test script error indicator"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure18.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>From this navigation tree, following mouse actions are
          possible:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Left mouse click: selection of a test script or a test
              suite</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Popup mouse click (triggered by right click on Windows and
              Unix): this action invokes a popup menu (Figure 19: Test script
              popup window) from which it is possible to:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Run the selected script</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Run the selected script in loop mode (can run the same
                  script in loop)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Debug the script (run in debug mode)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Generate documentation: selecting this option will
                  force the generation of the test documentation.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Edit the testscript in an external editor.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Open the testscript directory using a file
                  browser.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Copy test script (only available when a test script is
                  selected): the tester can then enter the name of the name of
                  the destination test script. This will copy the selected
                  script to the same parent directory of the source; This
                  action copies also the testdata.csv file.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Create new test script (only available when other than
                  test script is selected): this will define a new script into
                  the selected directory. This action generates also an empty
                  testdata.csv file.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Rename the testscript</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Remove the testscript</para>

                  <figure>
                    <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test script pop-up window"</emphasis></title>

                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure19.jpg"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test campaign view</emphasis></title>

          <para>This view displays the list of test cases (as done in the Test
          case view) from which the user can drag/drop test cases or test
          suites into a test campaign.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test Campaign main view panel"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure20.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Interactive view</emphasis></title>

          <para>In this view, the list of QTaste components are displayed with
          all accessible verbs associated to it. At any time, the user can
          invoke a method using this mode. This mode supposes that the SUT is
          already started.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Interactive main panel"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure21.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>From the selection view, the user can select the component
          from which the verb can be called (only components defined in the
          selected testbed are displayed).</para>

          <para>To start the interactive mode, click on the button "Start
          Interactive mode": this action will re-direct the log4j logs to the
          interactive panel.</para>

          <para>To invoke a verb, just double-click on it if there is no
          parameter. Otherwise, a single-click will display the python call
          associated to this verb with the parameter types as arguments,
          change them to the actual argument and click on the “Send” button to
          invoke the verb.</para>

          <para>The result of the call is displayed in the column
          "Result".</para>

          <para>The test data can be passed through the Test Data editor
          displayed in this panel.</para>

          <para>Please notice that some variable may be required in order to
          execute the command interactively (i.e.: INSTANCE_ID, etc.).</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Main panel</emphasis></title>

        <para>This panel has the goal to display the following
        information:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Status of a test case run;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Display of log4j logs;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Display and edit test scripts and test data files;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Display the test script documentation</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case documentation</emphasis></title>

          <para>The documentation of a test case is automatically displayed
          when a test case is selected from the selection panel (see also
          [1]).</para>

          <para>This documentation is automatically generated when
          modification on the TestScript.py has been identified. At any time,
          the use can force the generation of the documentation through the
          pop-up window accessible from the selection panel.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case source editor</emphasis></title>

          <para>This editor is displayed when the user selected a test case
          from the selection panel and the tab “Test Case source” is selected
          [2].</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test case source window"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure22.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>When the content of the file is modified the "*" is displayed
          to inform the user that modifications occurred in the file.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test script not saved"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure23.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>To save the modifications (all opened files), "CTRL-S" can be
          used or just click on the save button.</para>

          <para>Following popup menu is opened on the testcase source
          editor:</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test editor pop-up"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure24.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>If the user decides to run the test case being modified, the
          opened files are automatically saved.</para>

          <para>If the user selects another test case from the selection panel
          while files are modified without save, a confirmation dialog window
          is displayed asking the user if he want to save first the
          files.</para>

          <para>Test data (csv file) can also be edited by selecting "test
          data".</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test Data editor"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure25.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>A contextual menu is available in order to:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Add a variable: this will add a column into the
              csv.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rename variable: this will rename the currently selected
              variable.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove a variable: this will remove a column from the
              csv.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Add row: this will define a new test case.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Insert row: this will insert a row in the currently
              selected position.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Duplicate row: this will copy the currently selected
              row.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove row: this will remove a test case.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Save the changes into the csv file.</para>

              <figure>
                <title><emphasis>QTaste "Contextual menu of the Test data
                editor"</emphasis></title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure26.jpg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Test Requirements (NEW IN VERSION 1.2):</para>

          <para>QTaste can now store the list of requirements tested by a
          testscript in a simple xml files called “Req.xml”. This information
          will be used in test reports to show what requirements have been
          tested. The content of this file can be viewed and edited using the
          “TestRequirements” tab.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title><emphasis>QTaste "Test requirements tab"</emphasis></title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure27.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case result</emphasis></title>

          <para>This panel is automatically displayed when a run has been
          launched. This panel is divided into 4 parts:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Test run summary</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test case error identification</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test case error stack trace</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test case logs</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case logs</emphasis></title>

          <para>This panel displays the Log4J data as it also stored in the
          log file (&lt;test_specific_dir&gt;/log/QTaste.log, where
          &lt;test_specific_dir&gt; is the test specific directory specified
          in section 4.2).</para>

          <para>From this panel, the logs from LOG4J clients are also
          displayed: this feature is only available if the client application
          has been configured to be connected to QTaste log4J server.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Log4J panel"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure28.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Following information is displayed:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Time: time of the log</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Level: log4J level (Trace, Debug, Info, Warn, Error or
              Fatal)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Source: QTaste for all logs generated by the QTaste
              application, otherwise the name of the application as specified
              in the QTaste appender of the client application
              (log4j.appender.QTaste.application)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>@: The name of the logger</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Step: step of the current test (when applicable)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Message: log4j message</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>It is possible to filter messages using the check boxes. It is
          possible to filter log4j messages based on its level and the
          application generating the message.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>Test case execution navigation buttons</emphasis></title>

          <para>At upper side of the main panel buttons are displayed to give
          "quick" access to some actions.</para>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Navigation buttons"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure29.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Execute button: by clicking on this button, the current
              selected test script or test suite is executed</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Save button: by clicking on this button the current test
              script selected or test data is saved (and compiled through
              Python compiler)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Debug button: by clicking on this button, the execution of
              the test script is launched in debug mode (see QTaste debugging
              mode)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>"View Test Report": use this button top open the last
              generated (or generating) test report in your internet
              browser.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show test API button: use this button to open the main
              page in your internet browser of the QTaste test API
              documentation</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Stop button (displayed only when a test case is being
              executed): abort the test case execution. In that case the
              status of the test is set to "Not Available" with the reason
              "Test aborted by the user"</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <figure>
            <title><emphasis>QTaste "Stop button"</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure30.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste debugging mode</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Setting breakpoint</emphasis></title>

        <para>To set a breakpoint, just open the test script file and click on
        the line number panel where the script must be stopped.</para>

        <para>Remark: breakpoint can only be set at the TestScript.py
        file.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Setting a breakpoint"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure31.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Script breakpoint</emphasis></title>

        <para>When a test is executed in debug mode (click on"Debug test"
        button <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/image034.gif"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> ) the script is stopped at the selected
        breakpoint.</para>

        <para>Automatically, the QTaste user Interface displays the Test Case
        source window by highlighting the current execution line with the
        current python variable values.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Debugging variables"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure32.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Script break actions</emphasis></title>

        <para>The navigation buttons are updated to add buttons enable to
        continue the test script execution. Three actions are possible when a
        test script is break:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Continue: continue the script until next breakpoint is
            reached</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Step over: Step over the test script execution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Step into: Step into the test script execution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Stop: abort the test script execution</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Script break actions"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure33.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>QTaste build procedures</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste and testapi demo compilation pre-requisites</emphasis></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maven 2 has to be installed and available in the PATH
          environment variable (recommended version 2.2.1 or higher) can be
          downloaded from <link linkend="???"><ulink
          url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</ulink></link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Some libraries required by QTaste are not available on a
          public maven repository, so the qtaste_mvn_missing_dependencies.zip
          has to be uncompressed in the maven2 repository directory (i.e:
          ~/.m2/repository on linux). (Available on GitHub <ulink
          url="https://github.com/qspin/qtaste">https://github.com/qspin/qtaste</ulink>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste compilation procedure</emphasis></title>

      <para>The QTaste framework is composed of the kernel, demos and plugins
      test API.</para>

      <para>The kernel is generic while the test API depends on the interfaces
      of the SUT.</para>

      <para>For that reason, it is quite important to be able to recompile the
      test API especially if these interfaces are not stabilized.</para>

      <para>The QTaste framework is using maven “pom.xml” file to be built.
      This procedure does not take into account the installation of the SUT as
      this step are specific to the system to be tested.</para>

      <para>Retrieve the QTaste source code from GitHub available on
      <ulink
      url="https://github.com/qspin/qtaste">https://github.com/qspin/qtaste</ulink></para>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>QTaste compilation</emphasis></title>

        <para>To compile a simple unix/windows scripts can be used. QTaste is
        using ‘izpack” to create installation package.</para>

        <para>To ease the compilation procedure:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go into the &lt;QTASTE_SOURCE_ROOT&gt;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Launch the buildAll.cmd/sh script</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To create a new version of QTASTE installer:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go into the &lt;QTASTE_SOURCE_ROOT&gt;/izpack</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Launch the createInstaller.sh script</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If dependencies problems appear while compiling, please check
        that you uncompress the “qtaste_mvn_missing_dependencies.zip” in your
        maven repository directory.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>CSV file generation from Excel</emphasis></title>

      <para>The initial test data is an Excel file having the name
      “TestData.xls”.</para>

      <para>To generate the CSV file really used by QTaste, the QTaste Excel
      macro can be used (see (Optional) Installation of the Excel
      Macro).</para>

      <para>Using the “CTRL-S” key, the macro generates the CSV file according
      to the content of the Excel sheet. The macro is mainly responsible to
      use the correct data separator and convert numerical decimal value using
      a correct decimal separator into the CSV file.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Guidelines applicable for the test designer</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test scripts</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Guidelines and requirements to write test cases</emphasis></title>

        <para>Test designer and tester shall never assume that a verb will be
        executed and return the expected result.</para>

        <para>Test designer and tester shall never assume that a verb will be
        executed and return the expected result.</para>

        <para>Ideally, each verb should be validated by at least one check
        operation; this check operation is either another verb or a check done
        at the script level.</para>

        <para>First step is to validate your script before trusting its
        results.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Encoding</emphasis></title>
         <para>It is recommended to TestScript.py be encoded as UTF-8 when edited with external editors.
         Otherwise, if spectial charachers are used in documentation tags (e.g. @step)
         then qtaste will not generate the documentation properly.
         The QTaste source editor already save TestScript.py file as UTF-8.</para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test data</emphasis></title>

      <para>Test data are stored in a CSV file and can be edited either from
      the QTaste GUI (see Figure 25: Test Data editor) or in a Microsoft Excel
      sheet and saved back to a CSV file. An Excel macro can be used to ease
      the conversion of the Test Data into a CSV file (see CSV file generation
      from Excel).</para>

      <para>The first line of the file corresponds to the names of the test
      data and other lines correspond to test data values for a run of the
      test script.</para>

      <para>Test designer should try to find a meaningful name for test data
      and shall assure that all the test data have to be defined before the
      test is executed.</para>

      <para>There are some special test data associated with the QTaste test
      engine:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Test data name</entry>

              <entry>Comment</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>COMMENT</entry>

              <entry>This free text variable is used by the Test Designer to
              comment the values inserted in the line and their impact on the
              test at run time. This information will be used during the test
              report generation.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TIMEOUT</entry>

              <entry>This variable is used as a maximum time expressed in
              seconds for the test execution of one test row. By the default
              the value is 60 seconds. This value can also be set at the
              beginning of the script (in order to set the value for all test
              rows) or in the testdata file is value can differ from one test
              row to another.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FILE_*</entry>

              <entry>Column names starting with “FILE_” are automatically
              loaded by the Test Engine and their content can be retrieved by
              the scripts using the TestData (can be useful for data that need
              to be used on remote hosts).</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test data usage</emphasis></title>

        <para>The test data file is created in a CSV file named TestData.csv
        in the same directory as the test script itself. Following table
        provides an example of the content of this file.</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "test data usage"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure34.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>As already explained, the COMMENT test data is dedicated to
        define a free text comment associated to the row.</para>

        <para>The next columns contain test data values to be used by the test
        script.</para>

        <para>The test data can be changed inside the script itself using the
        python syntax (see Test data).</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test data encoding</emphasis></title>
         <para>Is recommended to CSV data file be encoded as UTF-8 when edited with external editors.
         Otherwise QTaste will not generate the documentation properly when special characters are used.
         The QTaste GUI CSV editor already handle CSV files with UTF-8 encoding for this purpose.</para>
    </section>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Guidelines applicable for the developer</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Introduction</emphasis></title>

      <para>This section describes the guidelines to be followed by the
      developer to develop or modify a component of the test API. The
      development of the test API consists of the following activities:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Define new test API components if necessary.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Define new QTaste verbs applicable for a defined test API
          component.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test API</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test API Components</emphasis></title>

        <para>Each component will be composed of:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a java interface defining the verbs available for the
            component, extending SingletonComponent or
            MultipleInstancesComponent interface from the
            com.qspin.qtaste.kernel.testapi package;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>java classes implementing the previous interface, we
            recommend to use the following convention for package names.
            com.&lt;company&gt;.qtaste.testapi.impl.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Verbs are simply java methods with no specific signature.</para>

        <para>For a component that must have only one instance, the java
        interface must extend the SingletonComponent interface and the
        matching implementing classes must have a constructor with no
        parameter.</para>

        <para>For a multiple instances component that must be identified by an
        id, the java interface must extend the MultipleInstancesComponent and
        the matching implementing classes must have a constructor with one id
        String parameter, the instance id and implement the getInstanceId
        method:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>public &lt;Component&gt;(String instanceId) { … }</term>

            <listitem>
              <para/>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>public String getInstanceId() { …}</term>

            <listitem>
              <para/>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>All component implementation classes must implement the
        initialize() and terminate() methods of the Component interface, which
        will be called on all components respectively before and after a test
        is executed. It can be e.g. used to connect to and disconnect from the
        SUT.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Exception handling</emphasis></title>

        <para>Test API should be compliant with the QTaste Exception handling
        policy in order to publish the appropriate test results.</para>

        <para>A verb may stop a test execution and set the test result to
        “failed” by throwing an QTasteTestFailException, or to "not available"
        by throwing any other exception.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Usage of TCOM</emphasis></title>

        <para>The test API implementation has the goal to communicate to the
        SUT. The way to communicate to the SUT depends on the kind of
        communication available.</para>

        <para>For this purpose, TCOM classes are provided and can be used by
        the developer.</para>

        <para>For example if you need to define a new JMX client to initiate
        the connection with the SUT using JMX, you can use the class
        “com.qspin.qtaste.tcom.jmx.impl.JMXClient”.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test API documentation</emphasis></title>

        <para>The test API can be documented using Javadoc. The documentation
        is generated through the provided doclet TestAPIDoclet, which is
        automatically run when compiling the testapi project (using maven). In
        order to get a complete documentation following doclets have been
        defined:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Only interfaces in the “com.qspin.qtaste.testapi.api”
            package, extending (indirectly) the
            com.qspin.qtaste.kernel.testapi.TestAPIComponent interface are
            documented</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The specific configuration of the component is specified in
            the interface documentation, using @config tags; the syntax is
            “@config CONFIG_NAME [Type] Description”, where Type is Integer,
            Double, Boolean or String</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Verbs are documented using standard Javadoc tags @param,
            @return and @throws</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Here below an example of the documentation:</para>

        <literallayout>/**
 * Compare the content of the specified defectID record with the expected value provided as parameter
 * @param defectID the identified of the record
 * @param shortDescription the title of the defect
 * @param longDescription the long description of the defect
 * @param assignee the identifier of the person assigned to this defect
 * @throws QTasteTestFailException If the content of the DB doesn't correspond to the specified values
 * @throws Exception Throw an exception in case of database connection errors
 */ String assignee) throws QTasteTestFailException, Exception;</literallayout>

        <para>From this example, following documentation will be
        generated:</para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis>QTaste "Example of generated Test API documentation"</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure35.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Logging levels</emphasis></title>

      <para>We defined some recommendations for the usage of logs severity
      levels:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Level of logs</entry>

              <entry>Usage</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FATAL</entry>

              <entry>Unexpected and unrecoverable errors. (no
              guarantee that the Test Engine execution will behave
              correctly)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>ERROR</entry>

              <entry>Unexpected error but the Test Engine can continue to run
              normally</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>WARN</entry>

              <entry>For example, to indicate that the test scenario is
              non-nominal.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>INFO</entry>

              <entry>Log what the Test Engine does</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>DEBUG</entry>

              <entry>Debugging purpose while using the test
              engine.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TRACE</entry>

              <entry>Debugging purpose during development phases of
              components.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>Configuration of the QTaste framework</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>General remarks about XML configuration files</emphasis></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The configuration files of the QTaste framework are stored in
          XML files located under the “conf” directory. The tag names used in
          the XML files are case sensitive. When a search for "smartsockets" is
          performed:</para>

          <screen>&lt;smartsockets&gt;&lt;/smartsockets&gt;   is valid
&lt;SmartSockets&gt;&lt;/SmartSockets&gt;   is not valid</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Properties can be used as “variable” to avoid repetition of
          configuration items.</para>

          <screen>&lt;sut_host&gt;myhost&lt;/sut_host&gt;     to define a variable sut_host
&lt;host1&gt;${sut_host}&lt;/host1&gt;      use the value of the variable sut_host
&lt;host2&gt;$(sut_host)&lt;/host2&gt;
&lt;host3&gt;AnotherHostName&lt;/host3&gt;</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Entity can be added to avoid repetition of settings or block
          of configuration.</para>

          <para>The following configuration file, called “component_web.inc”,
          shows a block of configuration.</para>

          <screen>&lt;!-- defines the Selenium component --&gt;
&lt;!-- &gt;${selenium_host} must have been previously defined --&gt;
&lt;Selenium id="TranslateApp"&gt;
          &lt;host&gt;${selenium_host}&lt;/host&gt;
          &lt;port&gt;4444&lt;/port&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://babelfish.yahoo.com&lt;/url&gt;
&lt;/Selenium&gt;</screen>

          <para>The following configuration file will reused the configuration
          block defined in the file “component_web.inc”.</para>

          <screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE configuration [&lt;!ENTITY components_web SYSTEM "component_web.inc"&gt;]&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
         &lt;multiple_instances_components&gt;
              The component of the irradiation controller will be copied here!!!
              &amp;component_web;
         &lt;/multiple_instances_components&gt;
&lt;/testbed_configuration&gt;</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XML elements are accessed by the QTaste kernel and Test API
          components. They can access nested element using a dot notation.
          This notation will be used in order to improve the readability of
          the configuration elements.</para>

          <screen>&lt;smartsockets&gt;
         &lt;host&gt;myHost&lt;/host&gt;
&lt;/smartsockets&gt;

will be presented as “smartsockets.host” in the description tables.</screen>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test engine configuration</emphasis></title>

      <para>Test engine configuration file allow the tester to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable/disable test retry when test fails</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Control the test report output formats</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Change parameters for the test reports or test campaigns
          doc</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the port for the log4j server (default is 4446), to
          which SUT processes can connect using a SocketAppender</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
      &lt;retry_test_on_fail&gt;true&lt;/retry_test_on_fail&gt;

      &lt;reporting&gt;
            &lt;!-- Reporting format  (XML or HTML, default to HTML) --&gt;
            &lt;reporters&gt;
                  &lt;format&gt;HTML&lt;/format&gt;
                  &lt;format&gt;GUI&lt;/format&gt;
            &lt;/reporters&gt;
            &lt;!-- Location of the HTML template --&gt;
            &lt;html_template&gt;conf/reporting/html/iba&lt;/html_template&gt;
            &lt;html_settings&gt;
                  &lt;generate_test_data&gt;true&lt;/generate_test_data&gt;
                  &lt;generate_steps_rows&gt;true&lt;/generate_steps_rows&gt;
                  &lt;report_stop_start_sut&gt;true&lt;/report_stop_start_sut&gt;
                  &lt;report_restart_sut&gt;true&lt;/report_restart_sut&gt;
            &lt;/html_settings&gt;
            &lt;!-- Location of the XML template --&gt;
            &lt;xml_template&gt;conf/reporting/xml/standard&lt;/xml_template&gt;
            &lt;!-- Location of the generated reports --&gt;
            &lt;generated_report_path&gt;reports&lt;/generated_report_path&gt;
            &lt;!-- Test campaign aggregated documentation parameters --&gt;
            &lt;test_campaign_doc&gt;
                  &lt;remove_step_name_column&gt;true&lt;/remove_step_name_column&gt;
                  &lt;add_step_result_column&gt;true&lt;/add_step_result_column&gt;
                  &lt;duplicate_steps_per_test_data_row&gt;true
                  &lt;/duplicate_steps_per_test_data_row&gt;
            &lt;/test_campaign_doc&gt;
      &lt;/reporting&gt;

      &lt;log4j_server&gt;
            &lt;port&gt;4446&lt;/port&gt;
      &lt;/log4j_server&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</screen>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Testbed configuration</emphasis></title>

      <para>All the information related to the testbed (like connection
      parameters, userid, password…) must be stored in the testbed
      configuration file which is located in the Testbeds subdirectory of the
      test specific directory (see Test specific directories).</para>

      <para>It is recommended to create a new testbed configuration file with
      a meaningful name for each new testbed.</para>

      <para>The following table explains the meaning of the xml tags used by
      the testbed configurations files.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Tag name</entry>

              <entry>Presence</entry>

              <entry>Meaning</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>control_script</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>This tag point to a script that will be used to start or
              stop the SUT once the test engine is started/stopped.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>testapi_implementation</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>This tag is used to group the list of component
              implementations to load for a specific testbed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>testapi_implementation.import</entry>

              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>

              <entry>This tag is used to specify the java package to be used
              for testapi implementations. The testbed supports multiple
              values for this parameter.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>singleton_components</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Special tag to describe the list of components of type
              “singleton” available in the testbed. But not the multiple
              instances components!!! Only singleton component should be
              described here.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>multiple_instances_components</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Special tag to define the list of components of type
              “multiple instances”. all the treatment rooms available in the
              testbed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>probe_manager</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>Special tag to define all the probes required to collect
              asynchronous events in the testbed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>probe_manager.probe</entry>

              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>

              <entry>This tag is used to specify the fully qualified java
              class name implementing the Probe interface required to collect
              asynchronous events.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?&gt;
&lt;testbed_configuration&gt;
        &lt;testapi_implementation&gt;
                &lt;import&gt;com.qspin.qtaste.testapi.impl.demo&lt;/import&gt;
                &lt;import&gt;com.qspin.qtaste.testapi.impl.generic&lt;/import&gt;
        &lt;/testapi_implementation&gt;
        &lt;control_script&gt;control_selenium.py&lt;/control_script&gt;
        &lt;multiple_instances_components&gt;
                &lt;Selenium id="BugzillaApp"&gt;
                        &lt;host&gt;localhost&lt;/host&gt;
                        &lt;port&gt;4444&lt;/port&gt;
                        &lt;url&gt;http://qtaste-bugzilla&lt;/url&gt;
                &lt;/Selenium&gt;
                &lt;Bugzilla id="BugzillaServer"&gt;
                        &lt;jdbcURL&gt;jdbc:mysql://QTaste-bugzilla:3306/bugzilla3
                        &lt;/jdbcURL&gt;
                        &lt;jdbcDriver&gt;com.mysql.jdbc.Driver&lt;/jdbcDriver&gt;
                        &lt;dbuser&gt;Taste&lt;/dbuser&gt;
                        &lt;dbpassword&gt;whataG00dN4m3&lt;/dbpassword&gt;
                &lt;/Bugzilla&gt;
        &lt;/multiple_instances_components&gt;

       &lt;singleton_components&gt;
             &lt;!—no singleton component in this testbed&gt;
       &lt;/singleton_components&gt;
&lt;/testbed_configuration&gt;      </screen>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Control scripts</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Description</emphasis></title>

        <para>As mentioned in Testbed configuration, QTaste provides a section
        in the testbed configuration to stop or start the SUT using a control
        script. This control script has a mandatory arguments "start" or
        "stop" and must return by an exit code different than 0 when
        failed.</para>

        <para>In the QTaste framework, it is possible to write those control
        scripts using some classes as provided by the
        tools/jython/lib/Lib/control_script.py python module. This python
        module has the purpose to give an easier way to write new control
        scripts but also to be OS independent.</para>

        <para>Please refer to control_script.py file for more details.</para>

        <literallayout>Here below example of control script stopping/starting the Virtual box and Selenium software:</literallayout>

        <screen>from controlscript_addon import *

ControlScript([
    VirtualBox("Bugzilla debian server",
                nameOfVBoxImage="QTaste-bugzilla",
                ),
    JavaProcess("Selenium Server",
                mainClassOrJar="demo/selenium-server.jar",
                checkAfter=5)
])</screen>

        <literallayout>The control script needs to initialize the class "ControlScript" with a list of actions to perform what is defined in an array.
The example here upper performs 2 actions:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start the VirtualBox virtual machine with the image called
            “QTaste-bugzilla”</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Launch a Selenium server using the JavaProcess</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <literallayout>Here below the classes defined in controlscript.py that can be used to defined new control scripts:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>JavaProcess: used to launch a java process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>NativeProcess: used to launch a simple native process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ReplaceInFiles: used to perform a "sed" action on
            files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rsh: to perform rsh command on remote host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RExec: to perform rexec command on remote host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rlogin: to perform Rlogin</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RebootRLogin: based on Rlogin and has the goal to reboot
            using RLogin a remote VME host</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Some examples</emphasis></title>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>JavaProcess</emphasis></title>

          <screen>JavaProcess("Selenium Server",
             mainClassOrJar="demo/selenium-server.jar",
             args="-specialOption option1",
             workingDir=sutDir+"/Selenium",
             checkAfter=5)</screen>

          <para>This example will start a java process using the jar
          file "selenium-server.jar" with arguments specified in args variable. This
          java process is being launched having as working directory equals
          to the variable sutDir/Selenium and the controls script will check if the
          process still exits after 5 seconds.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>NativeProcess</emphasis></title>

          <screen>NativeProcess("Windows control native Agent",
               executable="python.exe",
               args="demo/pywinauto-0.3.8/XMLRPCServer.py",
               workingDir=sutDir,
               checkAfter=5)</screen>

          <para>This example will start a native process using the executable
          file "python.exe" with arguments specified in args variable. This
          native process is being launched having as working directory equals
          to the variable sutDir and the controls script will check if the
          process still exits after 5 seconds.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>ReplaceInFiles class</emphasis></title>

          <screen>ReplaceInFiles(findString="day",
       replaceString="night",
       files="*schedule*")</screen>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>RExec class</emphasis></title>

          <screen>RExec(startCommand="start.csh",
      stopCommand="stop.csh",
      host="myhost",
      login="user",
      password="userPassword")</screen>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><emphasis>RLogin class</emphasis></title>

          <screen>RLogin(command='"sp cuStartup"',
       host=host,
       login="QTaste",
       log4jconf="Testbeds/ControlScripts/x.log4j.properties"))</screen>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>(Optional) Installation of Excel Macro</emphasis></title>

        <para>In order to ease the generation of CSV files, a Microsoft Excel
        macro has been developed. This macro file is located in the
        “tools\TestData” directory of the QTaste framework. To enable it, open
        the file QTasteMacros.xls with Excel and save it as an add-in (select
        Microsoft Office Excel Add-in (*.xla) format, add-ins directory will
        be selected automatically), then go in Tools menu, select Add-Ins,
        check “QTastemacros” and click on “Ok”.</para>

        <literallayout>This macro is generating a CSV file when you press “Ctrl-S” but the name of the xls file has to be called TestData.xls.</literallayout>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title><emphasis>QTaste scripting language guide</emphasis></title>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>General</emphasis></title>

      <para>QTaste scripts are written in Python language v2.7 and interpreted
      by Jython v2.7.0, (http://www.jython.org). Any Python feature supported
      by Jython v2.7.0 is thus supported by QTaste.</para>

      <para>A scan of all the (sub)directories from "test script" to "TestSuites"
      is performed. If there is a directory called pythonlib, it is automatically
      added, in the order of the scan, to the Python path.
      The developer can then import custom Python modules from those directories
      using the Python "import" directive.</para>

      <para>If some specific python modules have to be written, they can be
      added to the python class path just by adding the directory to the
      QTASTE_JYTHON_LIB environment variable. QTaste will automatically check
      this variable and use it if defined.</para>

      <para>This eases the reusability of the python scripts (see Module
      import).</para>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test API Components</emphasis></title>

        <para>Test API is accessed through components instances, which are
        obtained through the testAPI variable. This variable must be imported
        from the QTaste module e.g. using “from qtaste import *”, via
        get&lt;Component&gt; methods. For singleton components, no argument is
        required. For multiple instances components, an INSTANCE_ID test data
        is required to define the instance that will be used in the CSV file,
        in the script via the testData variable (see Test data) or by passing
        it as a named argument to the get&lt;Component&gt; method. The
        returned value can be tested to check if the component is present in
        testbed.</para>

        <literallayout>Get components instances examples:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>win = testAPI.getWindows()</para>

            <para>Defines win as the singleton Windows instance</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>selenium = testAPI.getSelenium()</para>

            <para>Defines selenium as the Selenium instance of the instance
            defined in the test data.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>selenium =
            testAPI.getSelenium(INSTANCE_ID=”TranslateApp”)</para>

            <para>Defines selenium as the Selenium instance identified by
            “TranslateApp”</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Testing the value returned by the get&lt;Component&gt; methods
        makes it possible to make a script usable in different
        testbeds.</para>

        <para>Example: myStub = testAPI.getComponentStub() if myStub: …</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Component verbs</emphasis></title>

        <para>Verbs are called directly on the components instances, using the
        required arguments.</para>

        <para>If a verb has a return value, it is returned by the call.</para>

        <literallayout>Call examples:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>selenium.click("link=New")</para>

            <para>On selenium, calls click(), which has an identifier</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>text = calculator.getText("Calculator", "Edit")</para>

            <para>On calculator, calls getText(), which has two parameters,
            and assigns its return value to the text variable</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Stopping test execution</emphasis></title>

        <para>A method named stopTest is also available on testAPI, to stop
        the test execution and set its status to “failed” or “not available”,
        with an associated message.</para>

        <para>Call syntax: testAPI.stopTest(status, message) where status is
        Status.FAIL or Status.NOT_AVAILABLE (Status must be imported from
        qtaste module, e.g. using “from qtaste import *”) and message is a
        string containing the message to report.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Test data</emphasis></title>

      <para>Test data are accessed through the testData variable, which must
      be imported from the QTaste module, e.g. using “from qtaste import *”,
      on which the following methods are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>String getValue(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the value of the test data with given name, as a
          string</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>int getIntValue(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the value of the test data with given name, as an
          integer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>double getDoubleValue(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the value of the test data with given name, as a
          double</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DoubleWithPrecision getDoubleWithPrecisionValue(String
          name)</para>

          <para>Returns the value of the test data with given name, as a
          DoubleWithPrecision</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>boolean getBooleanValue(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the value of the test data with given name, as a
          boolean</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>byte[] getFileContentAsByteArray(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the file content of the test data file with given name
          (starting with “FILE_”), as a byte array</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>String getFileContentAsString(String name)</para>

          <para>Returns the file content of the test data file with given name
          (starting with “FILE_”), as a string.
          By default, the content of the file is decoded using UTF-8 charset.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>String getFileContentAsString(String name, String charset)</para>

          <para>Returns the file content of the test data file with given name
          (starting with “FILE_”), as a string.
          The content of the file is decoded using the given charset. 
          (e.g: 'UTF-8', 'ISO-8859-1')</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void setValue(String name, String value)</para>

          <para>Sets the value of the test data with given name to given
          value</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void setIntValue(String name, int value)</para>

          <para>Sets the value of the test data with given name to given int
          value</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void setDoubleValue(String name, double value)</para>

          <para>Sets the value of the test data with given name to given
          double value</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void set DoubleWithPrecision Value(String name,
          DoubleWithPrecision value)</para>

          <para>Sets the value of the test data with given name to given
          DoubleWithPrecision value</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void setBooleanValue(String name, boolean value)</para>

          <para>Sets the value of the test data with given name to given
          boolean value</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>void remove(String name)</para>

          <para>Removes the test data with given name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>boolean contains(String name)</para>

          <para>Checks if test data with given name exists</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Calling a get value method (getValue, getIntValue, getDoubleValue,
      getDoubleWithPrecisionValue or getBooleanValue) with an inexistent test
      data name terminates the script execution and the test result is set to
      “Not available” with a message explaining that the given data doesn’t
      exist.</para>

      <para>Calling a typed get value method (getIntValue, getDoubleValue,
      getDoubleWithPrecisionValue or getBooleanValue) terminates the script
      execution if the data value can’t be converted to the specified type.
      The test result is then set to “Not available” with a message explaining
      that the given data has not the correct format.</para>

      <para>Calling remove with an inexistent test data name has no
      effect.</para>

      <para>DoubleWithPrecision is a class implementing a double with a
      specified precision. To use the constructor, it must be imported from
      the QTaste module, e.g. using “from qtaste import *”.</para>

      <para>Note that to test equality of an object of this class with a
      double or integer, you must explicitely use the equals() method instead
      of the == or != operators.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Logging</emphasis></title>

      <para>Logging is done through any Apache Log4j Logger, which can be the
      logger variable, imported from the QTaste module, e.g. using “from
      qtaste import *” and is a Logger named TestScript, or any Logger
      obtained using the log4j Logger class, e.g.: from org.apache.log4j
      import Logger logger = Logger.getLogger("LoggerName")</para>

      <literallayout>Most useful available methods are:</literallayout>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>logger.trace(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the TRACE level</literallayout>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>logger.debug(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the DEBUG level</literallayout>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>logger.info(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the INFO level</literallayout>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>logger.warn(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the WARN level</literallayout>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>logger.error(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the ERROR level</literallayout>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>logger.fatal(Object message)</para>

          <literallayout>Logs a message object with the FATAL level</literallayout>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The logger level is defined by the “log4j.category.LoggerName”
      property in the log4j.properties QTaste’s configuration file. Valid
      values are: ALL (log all messages), TRACE, DEBUG, INFO, WARN, ERROR,
      FATAL, OFF (doesn’t log any message). The log levels are ordered: TRACE
      &lt; DEBUG &lt; INFO &lt; WARN &lt; ERROR &lt; FATAL. A log method
      actually logs a message only if the log level is higher or equal than
      the logger level.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste exceptions</emphasis></title>

      <literallayout>The following QTaste exceptions may be imported from the QTaste module, e.g. using “from qtaste import *:</literallayout>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Exception name</entry>

              <entry>Meaning</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>QTasteException</entry>

              <entry>Base QTaste exception, from which all other QTaste
              exceptions are derived, resulting in a test “not
              available”.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>QTasteDataEcxeption</entry>

              <entry>Exception thrown in case of invalid data or argument,
              resulting in a test “not available”.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>QTasteTestFailException</entry>

              <entry>Exception thrown to make a test “fail”.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <literallayout>By catching an expected exception in the script, you can write a non-nominal test.
Here below is such an example.</literallayout>

      <programlisting><emphasis>try:
   myComponent.throwAnException()
except QTasteTestFailException:
   pass</emphasis></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>QTaste script</emphasis></title>

      <literallayout>Script documentation is generated through PythonDoc and an XSLT style-sheet.</literallayout>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test script description</emphasis></title>

        <para>The test script is described by adding a PythonDoc module
        comment at the beginning of the script, i.e. a comment starting and
        ending with a double sharp character.</para>

        <para>The name of the test script is the name of its containing
        directory and, as for javadoc, the first sentence up to the first dot
        is the summary and the next sentences up to the first tag completes
        the description.</para>

        <literallayout>The following tags must or may be added:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>@preparation (optional): the description of the test
            preparation</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>@data (optional): the data used by the test; the syntax is
            “@data DATA_NAME [Type] Description”, where Type is Integer,
            Double, DoubleWithPrecision, Boolean or String.</para>

            <para>DoubleWithPrecision is a double with a specified precision
            and is represented by the following string format:
            “doubleValue(precisionValue)” or simply “doubleValue” for a
            precision of 0.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <literallayout>HereHere below an example of the documentation:</literallayout>

        <programlisting><emphasis>##
# TestBugzilla - add a new record in the bugzilla database.
# &lt;p&gt;
# Script requests to add defects using the bugzilla web interface and
# the specified web browser and checks that
# the information are introduced correctly in the database.
# @preparation The bugzilla server has to be UP
# @data BROWSER [String] The selenium browser identifier
# @data BUGZILLA_LOGIN [String]  The bugzilla login ID
# @data BUGZILLA_PASSWORD [String] The bugzilla password
# @data SHORT_DESCRIPTION [String] The short description of the bug
# @data LONG_DESCRIPTION [String] The long description of the bug
# @data ASSIGNEE [String] The person that will be assigned to the bug
##</emphasis></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Steps description</emphasis></title>

        <para>Each step should be defined by a Python function, and described
        by a docstring comment (i.e. text between triple double-quotes inside
        the function), containing a @step tag describing the step and an
        optional @expected tag describing the expected results.</para>

        <literallayout>Here below an example of steps description:</literallayout>

        <programlisting><emphasis>def disconnectFromBugzilla():
   """
   @step        Disconnect from bugzilla
   @expected  The session should be closed
   """
   selenium.click("link=Log out")
   selenium.waitForPageToLoad("30000")
   selenium.closeBrowser()</emphasis></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Steps execution</emphasis></title>

        <para>Steps must be executed by calling the doStep() function or the
        doSteps() function, which must be imported from the QTaste module,
        e.g. using “from qtaste import *”, rather than calling the step
        functions directly. This enables QTaste to detect the beginning
        and end of steps, and compute the elapsed time.</para>

        <para>The doStep() function, allows to execute one step, passing an
        optional step id and the step function as arguments. The step id is an
        integer or a string containing only [a-zA-Z0-9_] characters, if not
        given the step number is used, starting from 1 for the first step. The
        signature of the function is:</para>

        <literallayout>  doStep([Integer_or_String stepId,] Function stepFunction)</literallayout>

        <literallayout>Here below an example of steps execution using the doStep() function, without step id:</literallayout>

        <programlisting><emphasis>doStep(connectToBugzilla)
doStep(createRecord)
doStep(checkDatabaseRecord)
doStep(disconnectFromBugzilla)</emphasis></programlisting>

        <literallayout>Here below an example of steps execution using the doStep() function, with step id:</literallayout>

        <programlisting><emphasis>doStep(0, connectToBugzilla)
doStep(1, createRecord)
doStep(‘1a’, checkDatabaseRecord)
doStep(‘2’, disconnectFromBugzilla)</emphasis></programlisting>

        <para>The doSteps() function, allows to execute a defined sequence of
        steps, passing a steps sequence and an optional steps selector as
        arguments. The steps sequence is a list or tuple of (stepId,
        stepFunction) tuples, stepId being an integer or a string containing
        only [a-zA-Z0-9_] characters. The steps selector is a string using one
        of the following formats:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>"[firstStepId-lastStepId]" to execute steps from firstStepId
            to lastStepId;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"[firstStepId-]" to execute steps from firstStepId to last
            step;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"[-lastStepId]" to execute steps from first step to
            lastStepId;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"[stepId]" to execute only step stepId.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <literallayout>If no steps selector is given, all steps of the sequence are executed.</literallayout>

        <literallayout>The signature of the function is:</literallayout>

        <literallayout>  doSteps(Sequence stepsSequence [, String selector])</literallayout>

        <para>Using this function allows reusability of a steps sequence if it
        is defined in a common module (see Module import), because it can be
        imported and used in several test scripts.</para>

        <literallayout>Here below an example of steps execution using the doSteps() function:</literallayout>

        <programlisting><emphasis>bugzillaSteps = [
  (0, connectToBugzilla),
  (1, createRecord),
  (2, checkDatabaseRecord),
  ('2a', disconnectFromBugzilla),
]

doSteps(bugzillaSteps)</emphasis></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Documentation generation</emphasis></title>

        <para>First of all, note that the documentation generation scripts
        must be run from the test specific directory containing the
        directories specified in section 4.2.</para>

        <para>To generate the documentation of a single test script, execute
        the command generate-TestScript-doc.bat(or .sh) with the test script
        file name as argument. This will generate an HTML file named
        TestScript-doc.html in the test script directory.</para>

        <para>To generate the documentation of a test suite, execute the
        command generate-TestSuite-doc.bat(or .sh) with the test suite
        directory name as argument. This will generate:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>HTML files named TestScript-doc.html for each test scripts
            of the test suite, aside the test scripts;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>HTML files named TestSuite-doc.html (main file, frameset),
            TestSuite-doc-list.html (list of test scripts) and
            TestSuite-doc-summary.html (summary of test scripts), in the test
            suite directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <literallayout>To generate the documentation of all test suites, execute the command generate-TestSuites-doc.bat (or .sh).</literallayout>

        <literallayout>To generate a Campaign test procedure document for a test campaign:</literallayout>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>execute the command generate-TestCampaign-doc.bat (or .sh)
            with the test campaign description XML file path as argument. This
            will generate an HTML file name &lt;campaignName&gt;-doc.html in
            the TestCampaigns directory;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><emphasis>Scripts reusability</emphasis></title>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Test script import</emphasis></title>

        <para>A test script can be reused by another script thanks to the
        importTestScript(), isInTestScriptImport(), doSubStep() and
        doSubSteps() functions, which must be imported from the QTaste module,
        e.g. using “from qtaste import *”.</para>

        <para>The importTestScript() function allows to import a test script
        in order to reuse its steps using the doSubStep() and doSubSteps()
        functions. void importTestScript(String testScriptPath) Imports the
        test script located in the testScriptPath directory and make its
        symbols available, including step functions and steps sequences, in a
        namespace named as the test case name, i.e. the name of the final
        directory of the test script. Actually, the code of the test script is
        evaluated except for the doStep and doSteps functions which are
        automatically skipped to avoid executing the steps during the import.
        testScriptPath - path to the directory of the test script to import.
        This path is relative to the parent directory of the current test
        script. It is advised to used forward slashes “/” as directory
        separator instead of backslashes “\” to make path platform
        independent.</para>

        <para>The isInTestScriptImport() function allows to check if code is
        executed during a test script import, i.e. during the execution of the
        importTestScript() function. It is useful to prevent execution of
        portion of code during a test script import.</para>

        <literallayout>   Boolean isInTestScriptImport()
      Returns True if code is executed during a test script import, False otherwise.</literallayout>

        <para>The doSubStep() function allows to execute an imported test step
        as a sub-step of the current step. It has the same signature as the
        doStep() function (see Steps execution).</para>

        <para>The doSubSteps() function allows to execute an imported sequence
        of test steps as sub-steps as a sub-steps of the current step. It has
        the same signature as the doSteps() function (see Steps
        execution).</para>

        <para>For example, the test script of the test case XYZ_01 reuse the
        test scripts of the test cases XYZ_01_02 and
        1_PreparationPhase/2_BDS/PBSV2_BDS_PREP_01.</para>

        <literallayout>Test script XYZ_01:</literallayout>

        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><emphasis>##
# Test Title - Description - Test case XYZ_01: Main flow.
# …
##

…

# set the MY_VARIABLE test data to False, because it is used by the XYZ_02
# test script but not declared in this test script
testData.setBooleanValue("MY_VARIABLE", False)
importTestScript("../1_ABC/XYZ_01_02")
importTestScript("../2_DEF/XYZ_01")

…

def step1():
   …

def step2():
   """
   @step Based on the test case XYZ_01: Main flow perform the nominal case.
   """
   doSubSteps(XYZ_01_02.mainFlow)


def step3():
   """
   @step Based on the test case XYZ_01: Main flow perform the nominal case
    (steps 1 and 3 to 5).
   """
   doSubStep(XYZ_01.step1)
   doSubStep(XYZ_01.step3)
   doSubStep(XYZ_01.step4)

# main flow steps, reusable in another test scripts
# doesn’t include step1 which is a initial step
# nor step5 which is a cleanup step
mainFlow=[(2, step2),
          (3, step3),
          (4, step4)]

resetSystem()
doStep(step1)
doSteps(mainFlow)
doStep(step5)</emphasis></programlisting>

        <para>Some function may use the isInTestScriptImport() function to
        avoid executing the a function when a script is imported:</para>

        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><emphasis>def function():
   if isInTestScriptImport():
       # test script is imported, so return immediately
       return
   …</emphasis></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>Module import</emphasis></title>

        <para>Test scripts can import common Python modules, allowing reusing
        the same code from several test scripts without duplicating it.</para>

        <para>For that reason, common modules have been created in the
        TestSuites/pythonlib directory. These common steps or common checks
        are implemented as classes and can therefore be derived and methods
        can be over-written for tests that need to modify the behaviour of
        some steps or to add new ones.</para>

        <literallayout>For example, the ABC module contains a CommonSteps class defined as follow:</literallayout>

        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><emphasis>class CommonSteps:

       def __init__(self, someValue):
          """
          @data SOME_VALUE [Integer] treatment room id
          """
           …
       …

       def aFunction(self):
          """
          @step      Start the function
          @expected  Description of the expected result
          @data SOME_VARIABLE [Double] A variable
          """
          self.function5()
          self.function8()

       …</emphasis></programlisting>

        <literallayout>This class can be used to create the test steps, as in the following example:</literallayout>

        <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"><emphasis>import ABC

class ABCSteps(ABC.CommonSteps):
       def performThis(self):
          """
          New step, not present in ABC.CommonSteps
          @step      Request the system to …
          @expected  After 5 seconds, system should be …
          """
          self.someCommands(self.someParam)
          time.sleep(5)
          self.someOtherCommans.('prepare.state:pending', 0)
          self.checkSomething(0)

steps = ABCSteps()

def prepareTest():
   """
   @step      Prepare the test and its parameters
   @expected  …
   """
   steps.prepareTest()

…

…
doStep(prepareTest)
…</emphasis></programlisting>

        <literallayout>It is also possible to reuse a defined steps sequence, by defining the steps and steps sequence in a common module.</literallayout>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
