<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>QTaste User Manual</title>
  <bookinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2012</year>
      <holder>QSpin SA</holder>
    </copyright>
    <revhistory>
  		<revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>02/10/2009</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>First version for Open Source Release</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
  		<revision>
        <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
        <date>29/03/2012</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Minor updates (QTASTE_JYTHON_LIB), update some url for sourceforge</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
  		<revision>
        <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
        <date>25/09/2012</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Minor updates for release 1.2</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
      <title>Why QTaste ?</title>
      <para>QTaste framework (QSpin Tailored Automated System Test Environment) is a generic test environment customizable to test different kind of systems. It can be used to test simple and complex hardware or software systems including a lot of different technologies. For that reason, the test api has to be “tailored” in order to enable the kernel to communicate with your system.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Purpose</title>
      <para>This document describes the installation and configuration steps of the “QSpin Tailored Automated System Test Environment” (QTaste). It provides useful information to the test designer and to the developer in order to define a new test script to be used by the QTaste framework.</para>
      <para>The test designer is responsible for writing test scripts based on the requirement documents. Associated to this task, the developer needs to provide a set of verbs that can be used by the script. The developer is responsible for the development of the newly defined QTaste verbs. Those activities must be performed with respect to the QTaste architecture.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Definitions, Acronyms and Abbreviations</title>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"></colspec>
          <colspec colname="c2" align="justify" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry>Term</entry>
                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Acceptance criterion</entry>
              <entry>Set of expected results expected at the output of the system when specific test data are provided. These can be exact values, ranges, probabilities, ...</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Actual outcome</entry>
              <entry>Contains a brief description of what the tester saw after the test steps have been completed. This is compared to the expected results in order to decide if the test is Success/Fail. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Agent</entry>
              <entry>Agents are active objects.They are capable of performing operations. Such agents may be software agents, hardware devices, or humans. They read inputs and generate outputs supposedly according to their requirements. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Automated testing</entry>
              <entry>Execution of tests without the intervention of the tester. Limited intervention of the tester for the introduction of results that are not available through interfaces, protocols and middlewares are possible during automated testing.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Control script</entry>
              <entry>A control script is a shell script able to start or stop a System Under Test (SUT).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Developer</entry>
              <entry>Person implementing some component, hardware or software and their stubs.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Environment</entry>
              <entry>(Sub-)set of systems, modules and components needed to perform a specific execution of a (sub-) set of operation of the original and complete system.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Expected results</entry>
              <entry>is a description of the results of the successful execution of a test case </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Failure</entry>
              <entry>in case of a failure, the software does not do what the user expects, according to the validation rule</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>GPL</entry>
              <entry>The GNU General Public License (www.gnu.org)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Input data</entry>
              <entry>is a set of values for input variables of a test case</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Intrusive, non-intrusive and low-intrusive test methods</entry>
              <entry>Intrusion means that the test is not using the public API of the tested component.
  Low-intrusion means that the behaviour of the component has been changed using the public API of a sub-component.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>LGPL</entry>
              <entry>The GNU Lesser General Public License (www.gnu.org)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Manual testing</entry>
              <entry>Execution of tests that are requiring the interaction of the tester or the test designer, to request some operation, to introduce test data, to introduce test results or to introduce validation rules.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Nominal cases</entry>
              <entry>Test case that is likely to happen during the nominal exploitation of the system.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Non-nominal cases</entry>
              <entry>Test case that may happen during the exploitation of the system during a fault or a degradation </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Open Source</entry>
              <entry>source code is provided</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Proxy</entry>
              <entry>A class functioning as an interface to another thing. The other thing could be anything: a network connection, a large object in memory, a file, or some other resource that is expensive or impossible to duplicate.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Requirement</entry>
              <entry>Is prescriptive statement of intent about the system to be, to be enforced by a single agent of the system-to-be through actuation of the variable under its control. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Simulated environment</entry>
              <entry>Environment that is using simulated and dummy (sub-)systems, modules and components.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Stub</entry>
              <entry>A piece of software or hardware that mimics the activity of a missing component</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>SUT</entry>
              <entry>System Under Test</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test API</entry>
              <entry>is the API providing methods to test a system or component and check the results</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test bed</entry>
              <entry>the aggregate of system under test, the test system, and the simulated environment. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test campaign</entry>
              <entry>is a predefined set of test suites or test cases that will be executed in order to get feedback about the quality of a  system.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test case</entry>
              <entry>is a scenario composed of a sequence of actions and validations under which a tester will determine if a requirement or use case upon an application is partially or fully satisfied. It may take many test cases to determine that a requirement is fully satisfied.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test data</entry>
              <entry>is a set of values for test cases, used as input data and as expected results</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test Designer</entry>
              <entry>Person designing the tests to be executed on the QTaste. This person has a good understanding of the system under test.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test environment</entry>
              <entry>Synonym of test bed</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test Extension</entry>
              <entry>is an extension to the Test API mainly used for Stress Test in order to « break » some components.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test log</entry>
              <entry>is a log of all the test verbs that have been executed and of their actual results</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test management tool</entry>
              <entry>is a tool used to define and organize test cases, test data, test suites to perform a test campaign. It helps the tester to do the follow up of the test results.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test report</entry>
              <entry>is a report containing the result of the execution of a test suite</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test script</entry>
              <entry>is a short program written in a test-dedicated programming language used to test part of the functionality of a software system. It mentions a set of steps that should be performed in order to execute the test case. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test suite</entry>
              <entry>is a collection of test cases</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Tester</entry>
              <entry>Person executing the tests defined by the Test Designer on the QTaste. Less skills are required than for the Test Designer, notably, he should not need to be an expert of the system under test in order to perform the tests.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Use case</entry>
              <entry>is a technique for documenting the requirements of a new system or software change. Each use case provides one or more scenarios that convey how the system should interact with the end user or another system to achieve a specific business goal. Use cases typically avoid technical jargon, preferring instead the language of the end user or domain expert. Use cases are often co-authored by requirements engineers and stakeholders.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Validation</entry>
              <entry>Checking that the behaviour of the system under test matches the expected behaviour, as described by its requirements. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Validation rule</entry>
              <entry>Rule checking if the expected behaviour and the actual outcome are identical or are matching acceptance criterion (parametric check)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Verb</entry>
              <entry>is an abstract definition of a functionality of the test API</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
  			</tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Overview of the QTaste framework</title>
    <figure>
      <title>QTaste “Overall system architecture overview”</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure1.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          An overview of the QTaste system architecture
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Requirements, taken from a requirement management tool or from a document are derived into Use cases and Test scripts specific to the SUT business.</para>
    <para>Test scripts correspond to a sequence of Test API calls expressed in python scripting language. Each call corresponds to an operation or to a validation. Test cases are the combination of test scripts and the associated data.</para>
    <para>An operation consists of a set of actions on the system under test. Validation consists of a check enabling the validation of a previous set of operations.</para>
    <para>In order to support a data driven approach, Test Data are stored independently of test scripts in a CSV (Comma Separated Values) file.</para>
    <figure>
      <title>QTaste “Example of python test script”</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          An example of python test script
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>QTaste “Example of test data”</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure3.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          An example of test data
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The table contains a list of columns names and associated values used by the Test scripts as inputs or expected outputs. These values are defined by the test designer. The values can correspond to a string input, numeric values, date, file path or any other kind of data format such as ranges or fuzzy information.</para> 
    <para>Each line of the sheet corresponds to a specific test with predefined data. It may correspond to the “nominal case” scenario or it could be a set of data that will lead to an expected failure (e.g. value out of range) for “non nominal case” scenarios.</para>
    <para>The combination of the test script and the test data allows the test designer to generate tests cases that will be run by the test engineer using QTaste. The creation of the test cases is a shared responsibility between the test designer and the developer, as specific formalism and functions might be required in order to allow the Test Engine to correctly parse and execute the complete sequences.</para>
    <para>Once the test cases are executed by QTaste, test report is generated giving the result of the test case execution.</para>
    <figure>
      <title>QTaste “Example of test report (part 1)”</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure4.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          An example of test report (part 1)
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>QTaste “Example of test report (part 2)”</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure5.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          An example of test report (part 2)
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>The QTaste Test-API parent</title>
    <para>Each testapi have to inherit of testapi-parent component. This is used to make the internal qtaste dependencies available to the custom testapi. It is also used to share the configuration of maven plugins. (like plugins for the testapi documentation, etc)</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Overview of the QTaste directory structures</title>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste kernel directories</title>
      <para>The following directories are located in the QTaste root directory.</para>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"></colspec>
          <colspec colname="c2" align="justify" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry>Directory</entry>
                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Testbeds</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains the testbeds configuration files</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Testbeds/ControlScripts</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains the control scripts associated to the testbeds</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>TestCampaigns</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains the test campaigns description files
</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>TestSuites</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains different test suites containing test scripts and test data</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>log</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains execution logs of the QTaste framework. It will be automatically created after the first execution of the Test Engine</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>reports</entry>
              <entry>This  directory contains the test reports generated by the Test Engine</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>testapi/target</entry>
              <entry>This directory contains the QTaste TestAPI jar and the generated HTML TestAPI documentation (in TestAPI-doc subdirectory)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
  			</tgroup>
      </informaltable>      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test specific directories</title>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Using QTaste framework</title>
    <section>
      <title>Test automation workflow</title>
      <para>In order to develop new test cases using the QTaste framework, it is really important to understand the following points:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">Identification of the architectural components of the SUT and their interfaces that will be used to perform the tests. Which technologies are required to communicate with the components interfaces?</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Are the components testapi already implemented in QTaste? Are the technologies required to communicate with components already supported by the QTaste?</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Do the components have the required verbs to perform the operations and checks?</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">What are the parameters required to perform operations on the components? Identify variables that can be used as “Test Data”</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">What configuration parameters of the testbed are required in order to use the components in any testbed configurations?</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Design the QTaste components interfaces and develop component implementations</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Develop the python test script(s)</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Add rows in the “Test Data” to test specific cases</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Execute the test suite(s)</listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">Analyse the test reports and report test failures</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Starting the test engine</title>
      <para>The command to execute a test suite or test script is:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtaste_start.bat (or qtaste_start.sh for Unix platform)
which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin directory in your path.</para>      
      <cmdsynopsis>
        Usage:<command><replaceable>command</replaceable></command>
          <arg choice='req'>-testsuite <replaceable>testsuiteDirectory</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='req'>-testbed <replaceable>configFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-sutversion <replaceable>SUT_version</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-engine <replaceable>engineFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-loop [<replaceable>count</replaceable> | <replaceable>hours</replaceable>h]</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="justify"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry>Option</entry>
                <entry>Parameters</entry>
                <entry>Presence</entry>
                <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>-testsuite</entry>
              <entry>testsuiteDirectory</entry>
              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>
              <entry>Specify the directory containing the testsuite(s)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-testbed</entry>
              <entry>configFileName.xml</entry>
              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>
              <entry>Specify the testbed configuration file to be used for the test.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-sutversion</entry>
              <entry>SUT_version</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify the SUT version that will be reported.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-engine</entry>
              <entry>engineFileName.xml</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify the engine configuration to be used for the test. By default, the file conf/engine.xml is used.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-loop</entry>
              <entry>None | &lt;count&gt; | &lt;hours&gt;h</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify to execute the test suite in loop, respectively infinitely, &lt;count&gt; times or during &lt;hours&gt;> hours.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
  			</tgroup>
      </informaltable>      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Starting the meta-campaign launcher</title>
      <para>A meta-campaign specifies a set of testsuites or testscripts to be executed on specified testbeds.  Optionally, the number of times they must be executed can be specified as well as the test data rows for which a test script must be executed.</para>
      <para>The command to execute a meta-campaign is:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtaste_campaign_start.bat (or qtaste_campaign_start.sh for Unix platform)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.
      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin directory in your path.</para>
      <cmdsynopsis>
        Usage:<command><replaceable>command</replaceable></command>
          <arg choice='req'>campaignFileName</arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-sutversion <replaceable>SUT_version</replaceable></arg>
      </cmdsynopsis>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="justify"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry>Option</entry>
                <entry>Parameters</entry>
                <entry>Presence</entry>
                <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry>campaignFileName</entry>
              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>
              <entry>Specify the name of the XML campaign file</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-sutversion</entry>
              <entry>SUT_version</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify the SUT version that will be reported.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
  			</tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>The format of the campaign file is the following:</para>
      <para>&lt;campaign name="Campaign_Name"&gt;
&lt;run testbed="testbedName.xml"&gt;
&lt;testsuite directory="testSuiteDirName"&gt;
[&lt;testdata selector="commaSeparatedListOfRowId"/&gt;] (optional, to execute scripts only for specified test data rows; row id starts at 1)
[&lt;count&gt;numberOfTimesOrHoursToExecute&lt;/count&gt;]  (optional, to execute in loop)
[&lt;loopInHours/&gt;]  (optional, if numberOfTimesOrHoursToExecute is in hours)
&lt;/testsuite&gt;
&lt;testsuite …&gt; … &lt;/testsuite&gt;
…
&lt;/run&gt;
&lt;run …&gt; … &lt;/run&gt;
…
&lt;/campaign&gt;</para>
    <para>Here below an example of campaign file:</para>
    <para>&lt;campaign name="Campaign example"&gt;
&lt;run testbed="enginetest.xml"&gt;
	&lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_SCRIPT"/&gt;
	&lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_KERNEL/QTaste_RES_06"&gt;
&lt;testdata selector="1,4,5"/&gt;
&lt;count>2&lt;/count&gt;
	&lt;/testsuite&gt;
	&lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_01"/&gt;
	&lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_04"/&gt;
	&lt;testsuite directory="TestSuites/TestSuite_QTaste/EngineSuite/QTaste_DATA/QTaste_DATA_05"/&gt;
&lt;/run&gt;
&lt;/campaign&gt;
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Starting QTaste graphical user interface</title>
      <para>The QTaste Graphical User Interface can be used in order to interact with the QTaste test engine and QTaste test campaign.</para>
      <para>The command to execute QTaste with its GUI is:</para>
       <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/ qtasteUI_start.bat (or qtasteUI_start.sh for Unix platform)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.</para>
      <para>To simplify usage, it is advised to put the ${QTASTE_HOME}/bin directory in your path.</para>
      <cmdsynopsis>
        Usage:<command><replaceable>command</replaceable></command>
          <arg choice='req'>-testsuite <replaceable>testsuiteDirectory</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-testbed <replaceable>configFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-engine <replaceable>engineFilename.xml</replaceable></arg>
          <arg choice='opt'>-loop [<replaceable>count</replaceable> | <replaceable>hours</replaceable>h]</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="center"></colspec>
          <colspec align="justify"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry>Option</entry>
                <entry>Parameters</entry>
                <entry>Presence</entry>
                <entry align="center">Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>-testsuite</entry>
              <entry>testsuiteDirectory</entry>
              <entry>MANDATORY</entry>
              <entry>Specify the directory containing the testsuite(s) to use when the GUI is started. So using this parameter, a test suite is launched.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-testbed</entry>
              <entry>configFileName.xml</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify the testbed configuration file to select, if not specified the last used testbed is selected.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-engine</entry>
              <entry>engineFileName.xml</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify the engine configuration to be used for the test. By default, the file conf/engine.xml is used.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-loop</entry>
              <entry>None | &lt;count&gt; | &lt;hours&gt;h</entry>
              <entry>OPTIONAL</entry>
              <entry>Specify to execute the test suite in loop, respectively infinitely, &lt;count&gt; times or during &lt;hours&gt; hours.This parameter is only taken into account when the parameter testsuite is also specified.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
  			</tgroup>
      </informaltable>      
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>HTML test report document</title>
      <figure>
        <title>QTaste "HTML Test reports”</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure6.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            An example of HTML test report
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Some additional remarks about HTML test reports document:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem override="bullet">The versions of the test scripts may be extracted from a version control tool (like subversion repository as example) during the execution of the tests. The version of will be reported only if:
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <listitem>the subversion command-client (“svn”) is available in the PATH</listitem>
            <listitem>testsuites are used in a svn repository and are a “tagged” as version. (rely on svn URL).</listitem>
            <listitem>The engine configuration file (conf/engine.xml) tag &lt;version_control&gt; is configured properly.(com.qspin.qtaste.util.versioncontrol.impl.SubversionVersionControl)</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The version will be set to “undefined” in all the other cases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem override="bullet">SUT version field is coming from either the SUT version field if the test is started from the QTaste GUI or the “-sutversion” parameter if started from the command-line.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test API Documentation</title>
      <para>The HTML Test API documentation is automatically generated by the maven Test API projects, in the target/TestAPI-doc subdirectory and is accessible from the GUI (see Figure XXX: Navigation buttons).</para>
      <figure>
        <title>QTaste "Test API documentation"</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure7.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            Test API documentation
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Additional Java libraries</title>
      <para>If for some reason, QTaste needs additional libraries, they can be specified through the environment variable QTASTE_CLASSPATH. These libraries will be automatically added to the class path and available during the QTASTE execution.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>QTaste Graphical User Interface</title>
    <section>
      <title>Starting tests</title>
      <section>
        <title>QTaste user interface startup</title>
        <para>The command to start the QTaste User Interface is the following:
${QTASTE_HOME}/bin/qtasteUI_start.bat (or qtasteUI_start.sh for Unix platform)
which must be run from the test specific directory containing the directories specified in section 4.2.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Testbed management</title>
        <para>For first startup a default testbed is selected, otherwise the last selected testbed during previous sessions will be selected by default.</para>
        <para>The user can change the testbed for which test must be executed by using the dedicated combo box displayed in the Information panel.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Current selected testbed</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure8.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Current selected testbed
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>When a testbed is selected, the current selection is stored in the preferences file (${QTASTE_HOME}/conf/gui.xml) in order to select it by default at the next launch.</para>
        <para>A contextual menu is available on this list to view or edit the testbed configuration file.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Testbed selection</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure9.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Testbed selection
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Test suite execution</title>
        <para>From the selection panel where the test cases are displayed, select the test case (Figure 9: test case execution) or test suite to execute (Figure XXX: Test suite execution), then press on the "Execute test"' button (Figure XXX: Execute test button).</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Test case execution</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure10.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Test case execution
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Test suite execution</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure11.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Test suite execution
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Execute test button</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure12.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Execute test button
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Test case result analysis</title>
        <para>The tab "Test Case Results" is automatically displayed when the executed test is started.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Test case results panel</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure13.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Test case results panel
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The test case results panel displays the following information:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <listitem override="bullet">Summary of the test case execution status;</listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Error details when test case is failed</listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Stack trace when test case is failed</listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Log4j panel displayed QTaste logs</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>When a test case result is failed (or Not available status), the corresponding icon is displayed. By selecting the row, the error details and the available stack traces will be displayed.</para>
        <para>From the Error details, the user can double click on the row and the Python editor will be opened at the line of the detected error. This is available for any python script except for the one having the file name "embedded_jython" which is built dynamically by QTaste during the test execution.</para>
        <para>By selecting test case result row, the Log4j panel will point to the first log associated to the test case.</para>
        <para>For more details about the use of the Log4j panel filters, please refer to Erreur : source de la référence non trouvée.</para>
        <para>It is possible to re-run a specific test case row (or several rows) using the popup menu on the test case result row, and select "Re-execute test(s)". Copy the details of the error in the clipboard or generate a test campaign from the test in errors.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Re-execute test(s) pop-up</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure14.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Re-execute test(s) pop-up
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste main window</title>
      <para>When the QTaste GUI application is started, the main window is displayed (Figure XXX: Main QTaste User Interface window).</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Main QTaste User Interface window</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure15.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Main QTaste User Interface window
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>This main window is split into the following panels:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <listitem override="bullet">Menu items</listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Information panel: this panel located at the upper side is designed to display useful information about the current configuration of the QTaste software</listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Selection panel: this panel is designated to select an action to be performed by QTaste. This panel is subdivided into three different tabs:
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
              <listitem override = "bullet">Test case tree view: this view displays the list of available test suites that can be executed by QTaste</listitem>
              <listitem override = "bullet">Test Campaign view: from this window, test cases can be added or removed to a test campaign</listitem>
              <listitem override = "bullet">Interactive view: this view allows the tester to execute QTaste verbs independently of a test script in order to validate its implementation or to observe the SUT behavior once the selected verb is called</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem override="bullet">Main panel: this panel is the main view of the QTaste GUI. This view differs depending on the selected view from the selection panel.</listitem>
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
              <listitem override = "bullet">Test case main panel: from this view the tester can view or edit test scripts, run a test suite, check the status of the test execution and also the logging generated by QTaste and its component supporting this feature.</listitem>
              <listitem override = "bullet">Test Campaign editor panel: from this view the tester can define or modify test campaign. The result of this edition will result of a xml file that can be used by the test campaign (see Starting the Meta-Campaign launcher); From this panel it is also possible to start a selected test campaign.</listitem>
              <listitem override = "bullet">Interactive panel: from this panel status and results of the calls done using QTaste interactive mode is displayed</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>          
      <section>
        <title>Menu items</title>
        <figure>
          <title>Help menu content</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure16.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              Help menu content
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Help menu</title>
        <para>Two menu items are available:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">About: display the QTaste information</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">User Manual: open Internet browser to this document in HTML version.</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Information panel</title>
        <figure>
          <title>Information panel window</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure17.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Information panel window</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>This panel displays the following information:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">Test suite currently set</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Test result directory location (relative to QTaste main path);</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Reporting format used (separated by “|” if different reports format generated by the test engine);</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Testbed config: indicates the current testbed selection. When no testsuite is being executed, it is possible to change the testbed using the combo box.</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Ignore control script: by selecting this check box, when test engine is started, the control script defined in the testbed configuration is ignored.</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Restart testbed button: from this button, it is possible to start the testbed using the control script as it is defined in the testbed configuration file. This button is disabled when “Ignore control script” is not selected or when a test is being executed.</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Stop testbed button: from this button, it is possible to stop the testbed using the control script as it is defined in the testbed configuration file. This button is disabled when “Ignore control script” is not selected or when a test is being executed.</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">SUT version is used to set the version of the “System Under Test”. This will be present in the generated reports.</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Selection panel</title>
        <para>This selection panel displays 3 different tabs depending on the desired action:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">“Test case selection view” to perform actions linked to test case edition and execution</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">“Test Campaign view” to define and edit test campaigns</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">“Interactive view” in order to execute tests using the interactive mode of QTaste</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
          <title>Selection panel</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure18.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Selection panel</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>        
        <section>
          <title>Test case selection view</title>
          <para>From this window, the tester can navigate through the different test suites. The tree view displays directories found in the main directory TestSuites. All directories containing a TestScript.py file will be displayed as a test script with the name of the directory where the script is found.</para>
          <para>In case no associated TestData.csv file is defined or in case the csv file is empty, an error icon is displayed on the test script.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Test case selection view</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure19.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Test case selection view</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure> 
        <para>From this navigation tree, following mouse actions are possible:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">Left mouse click: selection of a test script or a test suite</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">
              Popup mouse click (triggered by right click on Windows and Unix): this action invokes a popup menu (Figure XXX: Test  script popup window) from which it is possible to:            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
              <itemlist override="bullet">Run the selected script</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Run the selected script in loop mode (can run the same script in loop)</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Debug the script (run in debug mode)</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Generate documentation: selecting this option will force the generation of the test documentation.</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Edit the testscript in an external editor.</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Open the testscript directory using a file browser.</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Copy test script (only available when a test script is selected): the tester can then enter the name of the name of the destination test script. This will copy the selected script to the same parent directory of the source; This action copies also the testdata.csv file.</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Create new test script (only available when other than test script is selected): this will define a new script into the selected directory. This action generates also an empty testdata.csv file.</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Rename the testscript</itemlist>
              <itemlist override="bullet">Remove the testscript</itemlist>
            </itemizedlist>
          </itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
          <title>Test script popup window</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure20.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Test script popup window</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure> 
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Test campaign view</title>
          <para>This view displays the list of test cases (as done in the Test case view) from which the user can drag/drop test cases or test suites into a test campaign.</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Test Campaign main view panel</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure21.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test Campaign main view panel</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure> 
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Interactive view</title>
          <para>In this view, the list of QTaste components are displayed with all accessible verbs associated to it. At any time, the user can invoke a method using this mode. This mode supposes that the SUT is already started.</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Interactive main panel</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure22.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Interactive main panel</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>From the selection view, the user can select the component from which the verb can be called (only components defined in the selected testbed are displayed).</para>
          <para>To start the interactive mode, click on the button "Start Interactive mode": this action will re-direct the log4j logs to the interactive panel.</para>
          <para>To invoke a verb, just double-click on it if there is no parameter. Otherwise, a single-click will display the python call associated to this verb with the parameter types as arguments, change them to the actual argument and click on the “Send” button to invoke the verb.</para>
          <para>The result of the call is displayed in the column "Result".</para>
          <para>The test data can be passed through the Test Data editor displayed in this panel.</para>
          <para>Please notice that some variable may be required in order to execute the command interactively (i.e.: INSTANCE_ID, etc.). </para>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Main panel</title>
        <para>This panel has the goal to display the following information:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">Status of a test case run;</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Display of log4j logs;</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Display and edit test scripts and test data files;</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Display the test script documentation</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
          <title>Test case documentation</title>
          <para>The documentation of a test case is automatically displayed when a test case is selected from the selection panel (see also 1).</para>
          <para>This documentation is automatically generated when modification on the TestScript.py has been identified. At any time, the use can force the generation of the documentation through the pop-up window accessible from the selection panel.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Test case source editor</title>
          <para>This editor is displayed when the user selected a test case from the selection panel and the tab “Test Case source” is selected.</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Test case source window</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure23.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test case source window</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>When the content of the file is modified the "*" is displayed to inform the user that modifications occurred in the file.</para>          
          <figure>
            <title>Test script not saved</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure24.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test script not saved</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>To save the modifications (all opened files), "CTRL-S" can be used or just click on the save button.</para>
          <para>Following popup menu is opened on the testcase source editor:</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Test editor pop-up</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure25.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test editor pop-up</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>If the user decides to run the test case being modified, the opened files are automatically saved.</para>
          <para>If the user selects another test case from the selection panel while files are modified without save, a confirmation dialog window is displayed asking the user if he want to save first the files.</para>
          <para>Test data (csv file) can also be edited by selecting "test data".</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Test data editor</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure26.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test data editor</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>A contextual menu is available in order to:</para>
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <itemlist override="bullet">Add a variable: this will add a column into the csv.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Rename variable: this will rename the currently selected variable.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Remove a variable: this will remove a column from the csv.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Add row: this will define a new test case.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Insert row: this will insert a row in the currently selected position.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Duplicate row: this will copy the currently selected row.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Remove row: this will remove a test case.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Save the changes into the csv file.</itemlist>
          </itemizedlist>
          <figure>
            <title>Contextual menu of the Test data editor</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure27.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Contextual menu of the Test data editor</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>Test Requirements (<emphasis role="bold">NEW IN VERSION 1.2</emphasis>): 
QTaste can now store the list of requirements tested by a testscript in a simple xml files called “Req.xml”. This information will be used in test reports to show what requirements have been tested. The content of this file can be viewed and edited using the “TestRequirements” tab.</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Test requirement tab</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure28.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Test requirement tab</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Test case result</title>
          <para>This panel is automatically displayed when a run has been launched. This panel is divided into 4 parts:</para>
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <itemlist override="bullet">Test run summary</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Test case error identification</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Test case error stack trace</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Test case logs</itemlist>
          </itemizedlist>          
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Test case logs</title>
          <para>This panel displays the Log4J data as it also stored in the log file (<emphasis>&lt;test_specific_dir&gt;/log/QTaste.log</emphasis>, where <emphasis>&lt;test_specific_dir&gt;</emphasis> is the test specific directory specified in section 4.2).</para>         
          <para>From this panel, the logs from LOG4J clients are also displayed: this feature is only available if the client application has been configured to be connected to QTaste log4J server.</para>
          <figure>
            <title>Log4J panel</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure29.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Log4J panel</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>Following information is displayed:</para>
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <itemlist override="bullet">Time: time of the log</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Level: log4J level (Trace, Debug, Info, Warn, Error or Fatal)</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Source: QTaste for all logs generated by the QTaste application, otherwise the name of the application as specified in the QTaste appender of the client application (log4j.appender.QTaste.application)</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">@: The name of the logger</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Step: step of the current test (when applicable)</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Message: log4j message</itemlist>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>It is possible to filter messages using the check boxes. It is possible to filter log4j messages based on its level and the application generating the message.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Test case execution navigation buttons</title>
          <para>At upper side of the main panel buttons are displayed to give "quick" access to some actions. </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Navigation buttons</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure30.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>Navigation buttons</textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <itemlist override="bullet">Execute button: by clicking on this button, the current selected test script or test suite is executed</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Save button: by clicking on this button the current test script selected or test data is saved (and compiled through Python compiler)</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Debug button: by clicking on this button, the execution of the test script is launched in debug mode (see QTaste debugging mode)</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">"View Test Report": use this button top open the last generated (or generating) test report in your internet browser.</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">Show test API button: use this button to open the main page in your internet browser of the QTaste test API documentation</itemlist>
            <itemlist override="bullet">
            Stop button (displayed only when a test case is being executed): abort the test case execution. In that case the status of the test is set to "Not Available" with the reason "Test aborted by the user"
              <figure>
                <title>Stop button</title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure31.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <textobject>Stop button</textobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
           </itemlist>
          </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste debugging mode</title>
      <section>
        <title>Setting breakpoint</title>
        <para>To set a breakpoint, just open the test script file and click on the line number panel where the script must be stopped. </para>
        <para>Remark: breakpoint can only be set at the TestScript.py file.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Setting a breakpoint</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure32.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Setting a breakpoint</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Script breakpoint</title>
        <para>When a test is executed in debug mode (click on"Debug test" button  ) the script is stopped at the selected breakpoint.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Debug test button</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure33.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Debug test button</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Automatically, the QTaste user Interface displays the Test Case source window by highlighting the current execution line with the current python variable values.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Debugging variables</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure34.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Debugging variables</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Script break actions</title>
        <para>The navigation buttons are updated to add buttons enable to continue the test script execution. Three actions are possible when a test script is break:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
         <itemlist override="bullet">Continue: continue the script until next breakpoint is reached</itemlist>
         <itemlist override="bullet">Step over: Step over the test script execution</itemlist>
         <itemlist override="bullet">Step into: Step into the test script execution</itemlist>
         <itemlist override="bullet">Stop: abort the test script execution</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
          <title>Script break actions</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure35.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>Script break actions</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>QTaste build procedures</title>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste and testapi demo compilation pre-requisites</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <itemlist override="bullet">Maven 2 has to be installed and available in the PATH environment variable (recommended  version 2.2.1 or higher) can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html"></ulink></itemlist>
        <itemlist override="bullet">Some libraries required by QTaste are not available on a public maven repository, so the qtaste_mvn_missing_dependencies.zip has to be uncompressed in the maven2 repository directory (i.e: ~/.m2/repository on linux). (Available on SourceForge <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/qtaste/files/"></ulink>)</itemlist>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste compilation procedure</title>
      <para>The QTaste framework is composed of the kernel, demos and plugins test API. </para>
      <para>The kernel is generic while the test API depends on the interfaces of the SUT. </para>
      <para>For that reason, it is quite important to be able to recompile the test API especially if these interfaces are not stabilized.</para>
      <para>The QTaste framework is using maven “pom.xml” file to be built. This procedure does not take into account the installation of the SUT as this step are specific to the system to be tested.</para>
      <para>Retrieve the QTaste source code from source forge available on <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/qtaste/"></ulink></para>
      <section>
        <title>QTaste compilation</title>
        <para>To compile a simple unix/windows scripts can be used. QTaste is using ‘izpack” to create installation package.</para>
        <para>To ease the compilation procedure:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">Go into the &lt;QTASTE_SOURCE_ROOT&gt;</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Launch the buildAll.cmd/sh script</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>To create a new version of QTASTE installer:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">Go into the &lt;QTASTE_SOURCE_ROOT&gt;/izpack</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">Launch the createInstaller.sh script</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">If dependencies problems appear while compiling, please check that you uncompress the “qtaste_mvn_missing_dependencies.zip” in your maven repository directory.</emphasis></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CSV file generation from Excel</title>
      <para>The initial test data is an Excel file having the name “TestData.xls”. </para>
      <para>To generate the CSV file really used by QTaste, the QTaste Excel macro can be used (see (Optional) Installation of the Excel Macro). </para>
      <para>Using the “CTRL-S” key, the macro generates the CSV file according to the content of the Excel sheet. The macro is mainly responsible to use the correct data separator and convert numerical decimal value using a correct decimal separator into the CSV file.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Guidelines applicable for the test designer</title>
    <section>
      <title>Test scripts</title>
      <section>
        <title>Guidelines and requirements to write test cases</title>
        <para>Test designer and tester shall never assume that a verb will be executed and return the expected result.</para>
        <para>Test designer shall use checks to compare your expectation and the actual outcome. </para>
        <para>Ideally, each verb should be validated by at least one check operation; this check operation is either another verb or a check done at the script level.</para>
        <para>First step is to validate your script before trusting its results.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test data</title>
      <para>Test data are stored in a CSV file and can be edited either from the QTaste GUI (see Figure 25: Test Data editor) or in a Microsoft Excel sheet and saved back to a CSV file. An Excel macro can be used to ease the conversion of the Test Data into a CSV file (see CSV file generation from Excel).</para>
      <para>The first line of the file corresponds to the names of the test data and other lines correspond to test data values for a run of the test script. </para>
      <para>Test designer should try to find a meaningful name for test data and shall assure that all the test data have to be defined before the test is executed.</para>
      <para>There are some special test data associated with the QTaste test engine:</para>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="center" colwidth="1*"></colspec>
          <colspec align="justify" colwidth="2*"></colspec>
          <thead>
            <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>COMMENT</entry>
              <entry>This free text variable is used by the Test Designer to comment the values inserted in the line and their impact on the test at run time. This information will be used during the test report generation. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>TIMEOUT</entry>
              <entry>This variable is used as a maximum time expressed in seconds for the test execution of one test row. By the default the value is 60 seconds. This value can also be set at the beginning of the script (in order to set the value for all test rows) or in the testdata file is value can differ from one test row to another.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>FILE_*</entry>
              <entry>Column names starting with “FILE_” are automatically loaded by the Test Engine and their content can be retrieved by the scripts using the TestData (can be useful for data that need to be used on remote hosts).</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <section>
        <title>Test data usage</title>
        <para>The test data file is created in a CSV file named <emphasis>TestData.csv</emphasis> in the same directory as the test script itself. Following table provides an example of the content of this file.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>QTaste "Test data usage"</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="res/user_manual/figure36.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>QTaste "Test data usage"</textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>As already explained, the COMMENT test data is dedicated to define a free text comment associated to the row.</para>
        <para>The next columns contain test data values to be used by the test script. </para>
        <para>The test data can be changed inside the script itself using the python syntax (see Test data).</para>
    </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Guidelines applicable for the developer</title>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>This section describes the guidelines to be followed by the developer to develop or modify a component of the test API. The development of the test API consists of the following activities:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <itemlist override="bullet">Define new test API components if necessary.</itemlist>
        <itemlist override="bullet">Define new QTaste verbs applicable for a defined test API component.</itemlist>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test API</title>
      <section>
        <title>Test API Components</title>
        <para>Each component will be composed of:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <itemlist override="bullet">a java interface defining the verbs available for the component, extending <emphasis>SingletonComponent</emphasis> or <emphasis>MultipleInstancesComponent</emphasis> interface from the <emphasis>com.qspin.qtaste.kernel.testapi package</emphasis>;</itemlist>
          <itemlist override="bullet">java classes implementing the previous interface, we recommend to use the following convention for package names. <emphasis>com.&lt;company&gt;.qtaste.testapi.impl</emphasis>.</itemlist>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Verbs are simply java methods with no specific signature.</para>
        <para>For a component that must have only one instance, the java interface must extend the <emphasis>SingletonComponent</emphasis> interface and the matching implementing classes must have a constructor with no parameter.</para>
        <para>For a multiple instances component that must be identified by an id, the java interface must extend the <emphasis>MultipleInstancesComponent</emphasis> and the matching implementing classes must have a constructor with one id String parameter, the instance id and implement the getInstanceId method:
	<emphasis>public &lt;Component&gt;(String instanceId) { … }
	public String getInstanceId() { …}</emphasis>
	      </para>
        <para>All component implementation classes must implement the <emphasis>initialize()</emphasis> and <emphasis>terminate()</emphasis> methods of the <emphasis>Component</emphasis> interface, which will be called on all components respectively before and after a test is executed. It can be e.g. used to connect to and disconnect from the SUT.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Exception handling</title>
        <para>Test API should be compliant with the QTaste Exception handling policy in order to publish the appropriate test results.</para>
        <para>A verb may stop a test execution and set the test result to “failed” by throwing an <emphasis>QTasteTestFailException</emphasis>, or to not available by throwing any other exception.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Usage of TCOM</title>
        <para>The test API implementation has the goal to communicate to the SUT. The way to communicate to the SUT depends on the kind of communication available.</para>
        <para>For this purpose, TCOM classes are provided and can be used by the developer.</para>
        <para>For example if you need to define a new JMX client to initiate the connection with the SUT using JMX, you can use the class <emphasis>“com.qspin.qtaste.tcom.jmx.impl.JMXClient”</emphasis>.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Test API documentation</title>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Logging levels</title>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Configuration of the QTaste framework</title>
    <section>
      <title>General remarks about XML configuration files</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test engine configuration</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Testbed configuration</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Control scripts</title>
      <section>
        <title>Description</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Some examples</title>
        <section>
          <title>JavaProcess</title>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>NativeProcess</title>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>ReplaceInFiles class</title>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>RExec class</title>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>RLogin class</title>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>(Optional) Installation of Excel Macro</title>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>QTaste scripting language guide</title>
    <section>
      <title>General</title>
      <section>
        <title>Test API Components</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Component verbs</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Stopping test execution</title>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test data</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste exceptions</title>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>QTaste script</title>
      <section>
        <title>Test script description</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Steps description</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Steps execution</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Documentation generation</title>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Scripts reusability</title>
      <section>
        <title>Test script import</title>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Module import</title>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
